<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A cabinet of jewels, or, A glimps [sic] of Sions glory written by William Dyer ...</title>
            <author>Dyer, William, d. 1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15940</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13353547</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13353547</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99213</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 787:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A cabinet of jewels, or, A glimps [sic] of Sions glory written by William Dyer ...</title>
                  <author>Dyer, William, d. 1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 146 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:99213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>line engraving portrait of William Dyer</figDesc>
                  <head>WILLIAM DYER <hi>Preacher of the Goſpell Aetat: 27: 1663</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CABINET OF JEWELS. OR, A GLIMPS OF <hi>SIONS</hi> GLORY. Written by WILLIAM DYER, late Preacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Cheſham</hi> and <hi>Chouldsbury,</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this prophecy, and keep thoſe things that are written therein, for the time is at hand.<bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 1.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99213:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99213:2"/>
            <head>TO Thoſe of <hi>Chouldsbury</hi> Pariſh, Together with all others who did attend conſtantly upon the Word of God there Preached.</head>
            <head type="sub">Grace, Mercy, and Peace be multiplyed from God the Father, through our Lord Jeſus Christ.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Early Beloved, They that love God dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are dearly beloved of God, dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of Chriſt, dearly beloved of Angels, dearly beloved of Saints; they are beloved of all, and have the love of all, whoſe love is worth the having.</p>
            <p>O my dear Friends, I cannot think of you and your condition,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99213:3"/>but it fills my eyes with water, and my heart with griefe; and with <hi>Jeremy</hi> I wiſh, <hi>O that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountaine of Tears, that I might weep day and night for the ſlain of the Daughter of my people,</hi> Jeremiah 9.1. Oh that I am conſtrained to be from you, whom I could live and dye with, ſpend and be ſpent for ſo deare a people as you are; I would chuſe to be doing the work to which I was called, amongſt you, rather then any where elſe, if I might. I ſhould not count my Life dear to me, ſo that I might have the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to preach Chriſt to you for your edification and ſalvation. I hope your Conſciences will bear me witneſſe, that whileſt I was with you, I Laboured as much as in me lay, to be a helper of your joy, not to Lord it over your faith; and I bleſs God I can with a good conſcience ſafely ſay, I have cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99213:3"/>no mans Gold, nor Silver, as you your ſelves know: I could do very much for you, but I dare not ſin againſt God and my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>But my dear Brethren, Though they have ſeparated us one from the other, they cannot ſeparate our hearts; I hope there will never be a ſeparation of our loves, but that will ſtill continue; if we do not ſee one another, yet we may love one another, and pray for one another: And now my deſire is, that my pen may reach you, though my voice cannot reach you.</p>
            <p>That I may ſtill approve the ſincerity of my love to you, I ſhall give you twenty Directions for the right ordering of your Lives and converſations in theſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſinful times; that you may live in Heaven whileſt you are on the Earth, and come to Heaven when you ſhall leave the Earth.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99213:4"/>
            <p n="1">I. Firſt, Loath ſin, and leave ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that covereth his ſins ſhall not proſper, but whoſoever Confeſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall have mercy,</hi> Prov. 28.13. <hi>If we confeſs our ſins he is faithfull and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs,</hi> 1 John 1.9. There muſt be falling out with our ſins, before there be falling off from our ſins; there muſt be a loathing of ſin in our affections, before there be a leaving of ſin in our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations. Oh is it not a thouſand times better to part with ſinne, though never ſo ſweet? than to part with God, and Chriſt, and Heaven? one of them you muſt do. One ſin will damn a Soul out of Chriſt, but no ſin can damn a Soul in Chriſt: Sin is the evill of evils, it is worſe then the Devill for its that that made the Devil to be a Devil. O the love of ſin, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99213:4"/>the lack of grace will ruin and deſtroy your ſouls for ever: It is better not to be, than to be a ſinner; better to be no people, than not to be the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Oh therefore kill ſin, that ſin may not kill you: mourn for ſin, and flye from ſin: do not commit new ſins, but repent of old ſins, Ezek. 36.31. <hi>You ſhall loath your ſelves in your own ſight for your iniquities.</hi> O poor ſoul, haſt thou not ſerved the fleſh, and the Devil long enough? Yea, haſt thou not had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of ſin? is it ſo good to thee, or ſo profitable for thee? Oh what a place will you be ſhortly in of joy or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! Oh what a ſight will you ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee in Heaven or Hell! Oh what thoughts will ſhortly fill your hearts with unſpeakable delights or horror! what work will you be imployed in, to praiſe the Lord with Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or to cry out in fire unquenchable with Divels? Oh therefore dye unto ſin, confeſs it, mourn for it, and be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of it, hate it, and loath it, and flye from it, as from a Serpent; and though
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99213:5"/>your ſins are more then you can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, yet they are not more then God can pardon.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Secondly, Put off the old man, and put on the new.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eye not one to another, ſeeing ye have put off the old man with his deeds, and have put on the new man, which is renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in knowledge after the Image of him that created him,</hi> Col. 3.9, 10. <hi>And that ye put on the new man, which after God is created in Righteouſneſs and Holineſſe,</hi> Epheſ. 1.14. <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus neither circumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but a new creature,</hi> Gal. 6.15. <hi>As new born Babes deſire the ſincere milk of the Word, that they may grow thereby,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2.2. <hi>Therefore if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature; old things are paſt away; behold all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. A new under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, a new will, new deſires, new love, new delights, new thoughts, new words, new company, and a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; he is not what he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. O dear friends, be new Creatures,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99213:5"/>that you may be glorious Creatures: We can call nothing in Heaven ours, till Chriſt be ours. Without regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there is no ſalvation; <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, except yea be converted, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as little children, ye cannot enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdone of Heaven,</hi> John 3.3. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto thee, except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdome of God.</hi> You have heard much of God, Chriſt, and Heaven with your ears, but this will not bring you to Heaven, unleſſe you have much of God, Chriſt, &amp; Heaven in your hearts; you muſt be able to ſay, I was once a ſlave, but now a ſon; once I was dead, but now I am alive; once I was in darkneſſe, but now I am light in the Lord; once I was a child of wrath, an Heir of Hell, but now I am an Heir of Heaven; once I was under the ſpirit of bondage, but now I am under the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of adoption. A true Believer lives in the Lord, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. On the Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Luke.</hi> 20.38. From the Lord, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.57. To the Lord, <hi>Romans</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.8.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99213:6"/>With the Lord, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 13.4.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Thirdly, Make your peace, with the Prince of peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. Pſal. 2.12. <hi>Kiſs the Son, leaſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way: when his wrath is kindled but a little, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi> O do not lift up your hand againſt the Son, but kiſſe the Son.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Let his Will be your Rule;</item>
               <item>His Spirit your Guide;</item>
               <item>His precepts your practices;</item>
               <item>His decrees your delights;</item>
               <item>His choſen ones, your choiceſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions.</item>
               <item>Submit to his Goſpel and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Oh Sirs, make your peace with God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>There is a fourfold Peace.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, There is a peace external: this peace is with men.</item>
               <item>Secondly, There is peace ſupernal: that is peace with God.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, There is peace internall: that is peace with Conſcience.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, There is peace eternall:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99213:6"/>and this is peace in Heaven, Pſal. 37.37. <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>If you have peace with God, the world, and the Devil cannot hurt you: <hi>And upon the glory ſhall be a defence,</hi> Iſa. 4.5. Believers have God for their Guide and Guard; he that meddles with the Saints of God, aſſaults God himſelf, Zech. 2.8. <hi>He that toucheth you, toucheth the Apple of mine eye.</hi> He that lifts up his hand againſt them, lifts up his hand againſt God; though they have many enemies, yet they have one friend that hath more ſtrength then all their enemies. A ragged Saint is dearer to God, then a glittering Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour that wants grace. O make your peace with the Prince of peace; that in this life you may have aſſurance of eternal life, that eternal death may not be your portion in the other life.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Fourthly, Make Religion your main buſineſs, and not a by buſineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore the rather, Brethren, give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to make your Calling and Election
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99213:7"/>ſure; for if ye doe theſe things, ye ſhall never fall,</hi> 2 Peter 1.10. <hi>Work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> Phil. 2.12. <hi>But ſeek ye firſt the Kingdome of God, and his righteouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you,</hi> Math. 6.23. Oh, why is the glory of this world ſo much regarded, but becauſe the Glory of Heaven is ſo little minded. Oh, what is an Earthly Kingdome in compariſon of the Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? the Angels themſelves, though they are glorious Spirits, yet they are Miniſtring Spirits.</p>
            <p>Do not moſt men in the world make light of God, and Chriſt, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Heaven, and their precious ſouls? <hi>And he ſent forth his ſervants to call them that were bidden to the wedding, and they would not come: Again he ſent forth other ſervants, ſaying, tell them that are bidden, Behold, I have prepared my Dinner; my Oxen and my Fatlings are killed, and all things are ready: Come unto the Marriage. But they made light of it, and went their way, one to his Farm,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99213:7"/>another to his Merchandize,</hi> Math. 22.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Wretched Wordlings make Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a by-buſineſs; they will hear, read, and pray when they have nothing elſe to doe: Oh that ſuch men did but know what everlaſting Glory, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting torments are: would they then do as they do? Oh that they did but know the worth of their Souls, and the want of a Saviour; the ſhortneſſe of their time, and the greatneſs of their work: would they then neglect God and their own ſouls as they do?</p>
            <p>Oh Friends, Let me beſeech you to whom I write, to make Religion your main buſineſſe, hearing, reading, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, believing and doing, your maine buſineſſe. <hi>Labour not for the meat which periſheth, but for that meat which endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth unto everlaſting life, which the Son of man ſhall give unto you; for him hath God the father ſealed,</hi> Joh. 6.27.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Fifthly, Doe nothing in this World, but what you can anſwer in another World.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99213:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For we muſt all appear before the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>In the day when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpel,</hi> Rom. 2.16. <hi>He hath appointed a day in which he will judg the world in righteouſneſſe, by that man whom he hath ordained,</hi> Acts 17.31. <hi>For God ſhall bring every work to judgement, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good or whether it be evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.14. Oh for the Lords ſake, my Dear Brethren, Let nothing be done by you in this world, but what may be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in another world.</p>
            <p>Many men doe that in this world which they cannot in another world; Now they contemne God, blaſpheme God, rebel againſt God, go a whoring from God, and perſecute the Beloved of God: Inſtead of protecting the Saints, impriſon the Saints; and are more for cruſhing them, than comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them: inſtead of viſiting them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99213:8"/>vilifie them; and inſtead of affecting them, afflict them, and <hi>eat them up as they eat bread,</hi> Pſal. 14.4. And will not ſuffer them to worſhip the true God in Spirit and in truth; but
<list>
                  <item>Mock them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11:36.</item>
                  <item>Threaten them, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.29.</item>
                  <item>Accuſe them, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5.</item>
                  <item>Slander them, <hi>Math.</hi> 1.11.</item>
                  <item>Curſe them, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.44.</item>
                  <item>Beat them, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.40.</item>
                  <item>Impriſon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.3.</item>
                  <item>Plunder them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34.</item>
                  <item>Baniſh them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</item>
                  <item>And Murder them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All this the poor innocent ſuffer, whilſt ſwearing, curſing, whoring rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, blaſpheming, drunkenneſs; and gluttoning, and all manner of debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, yea, murder it ſelf walks unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the ſtreets; and only <hi>he that departs from evill makes himſelf a prey.</hi> What wonder then if ſuch as theſe ſhall one day hide themſelves in Dens and Holes, <hi>and cry to the Rocks and Mountains to fall on them, and hide them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99213:9"/>from the face of him that ſits on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 6.15.36. Oh what will Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors do, <hi>when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall appear in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that knew him not, and obeyed not his Goſpel,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1:8. Will they not then be dumb and ſpeechleſſe, and have never a word to ſay for themſelves, as that man that had not on his Wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.12.</p>
            <p>But Oh Beloved, <hi>Let that grace that hath appeared to all men, teach us to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, that we may live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent World,</hi> Tit. 2.11.12. following the Lamb, reſiſting Satan, ſhuning ſin, and ſeparating from the world.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Sixthly, Make the Word of God your Rule, and the Spirit of God your Guide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony: if they ſpeak not according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> Iſa. 8.20. <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, whereunto ye doe well that ye take
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99213:9"/>heed, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarre ariſe in your hearts,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19. <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> 2 Tim: 3.16. <hi>Howbeit, when the ſpirit of truth is come, he will guide you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth; for he ſhall not ſpeak of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but whatſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak, and he will ſhew you things to come,</hi> John 16.13. The Scripture is a Rule before us, to ſhew us where we muſt go; the Spirit is a word behind us, to enable us to go according to the Directions of that word: The Word of God is a Compaſs, by which we are to Ship our Courſe; the Spirit is the great Pilot that ſteers us in this courſe. We have no eyes to ſee the Word, till the Spirit enlighten them; we have no ears to hear the Word, till the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit open them, we have no hearts to obey the Word, till the Spirit bow and encline them. By the Word of God we know the mind of the Spirit; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99213:10"/>and by the efficacy of the ſpirit we feel the efficacy of the Word: The Word of God ſhews us the way; and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God leads us in that way which the WOrd points out. The Spirit of God is able to expound the Word of God, and to make it plain to our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. The Holy Ghoſt is the Churches Interpreter; he gives the Scripture, and he can reveal unto us the ſenſe and meaning of the Scripture. The word is Gods Counſellour, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the path in which we are to walk; the Spirit is the Counſel of God, that teacheth us how to walk in that path. The word is a Chryſtall-Glaſs, which ſhewes us our duty; the Spirit gives us ſight to ſee our duty; If God had not put his Spirit into our hearts, as well as his word into our mouths, we ſhould never have arrived at the fair Haven of peace. <hi>Auſtin</hi> calls the Scriptures, <hi>The Epiſtle of God to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> by which we underſtand the very heart of God. God Almighty hath in the ſecret Scriptures, as it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowelled
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99213:10"/>himſelf, and unfolded all his Counſel to the Creatures, as far as it is neceſſary to be known, for their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and guidance to everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>There be many that walke by falſe Rules.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, Some by Opinions,</item>
               <item>Secondly, Some by Cuſtomes.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, Some by Providence.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, Some by Conſcience.</item>
               <item>Fifthly, Some by their own Reaſon.</item>
               <item>Sixthly, Some by mens examples.</item>
               <item>Seventhly, Some by their Luſts.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But, O my dear friends, let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to walke by none of theſe falſe Rules; but keep cloſe to the word and ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Seventhly, Be faithfull and fruitful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, my beloved brethren, Be ye ſtedfaſt and unmoveble, alwayes abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as you know, your labour is not in vain,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.58. Every Tree that beareth not good fruit, is hewn down, and caſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99213:11"/>into the fire. Chriſtians muſt be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and not ſlothful: See that you bring forth good fruit, and much fruit.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Sincerity;</hi> which is not a ſingle Grace, but the ſoul of all Graces: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thou deſireſt truth in the inward parts</hi> Pſal: 51:6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Humility;</hi> A Grace moſt prevailing with God for the obtaining of all Graces. <hi>Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart, and ye ſhall find reſt unto your ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Prudence.</hi> The patient Chriſtian is the beſt for waiting, but the prudent Chriſtian is the beſt for work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Be ye wiſe as Serpents, and harmleſs as Doves,</hi> Mat. 10.16. We muſt have innocency with our wiſdome, elſe our wiſedome is but craftineſſe; and we muſt have wiſdome with our innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, elſe our innocency is but weakneſs; we muſt have the harmleſneſſe of the Dove, that we may not wrong others; and we muſt have the prudence of the Serpent, that others may not abuſe and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99213:11"/>circumvent us: Not to wrong the truth by ſilence, here is the innocency of the Dove: not to betray our ſelves by raſhneſſe; here is the wiſdome of the Serpent.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Patience. Here is the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of the Saints,</hi> Rev. 13.10. Rev. 14.12. The way to bring the world under us, is for us to be patient under them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Self-denyal. If any man will come after me, let him deny himſelf, and take up his croſſe and follow me,</hi> Math. 16.24.</p>
            <p>Be faithful in your promiſes, &amp; in your purpoſes; by faithful to the wayes of God, and cauſe of God; O do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Lamb, and end with the Beaſt; but <hi>be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of life,</hi> Rev. 2.20. Keep your Lights burning, your Lamps ſhining, your Loyns girded, your Conſciences wakned, your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unſtained, and your Spirituall Armour conſtantly on, and cloſely girt:</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99213:12"/>
            <p n="8">VIII. Eightly, Have a care of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting and believing the worlds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of the people of God.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that have a good conſcience, have not alwayes a good name. The people of God in this life are called the troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſeditious, rebellious, and what not? An old device of that old ſerpent, to perſwade the troublers of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon <hi>Elijah,</hi> the Charret of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.17. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2 12. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> for ſpeaking againſt their ſins and wickedneſſes, and denouncing <hi>Gods</hi> judgements againſt them, is judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worthy of death, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 26.8.9. So <hi>Jerem.</hi> 38.4. The wicked Nobles peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the King to murder him, under the pretence, that he ſought not the good of the people, but the hurt. So <hi>Amos</hi> for ſpeaking againſt the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Kings Court, is charged with treaſon againſt the Kings perſon, <hi>Amos</hi> 7.10.13. So <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> for preaching up the Kingly power of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, are accuſed by the envious <hi>Jewes</hi> and rude multitude, for turning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99213:12"/>the world upſide down, and breaking the decrees of <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Yea, Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had this laid to his Charge: mark what the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſay of him: <hi>And they began to accuſe him, ſaying, We found this Fellow perverting the Nation, and forbidding to give tribute to Caeſar, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he himſelfe is Chriſt a King,</hi> Luke 23.2. Math. 72.18. And for this have the ſervants of God in all Ages been accuſed and perſecuted, killed and ſtoned, <hi>Math.</hi> 27:37. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.52. Now if they did ſo to the green Tree, no wonder if they do it to the dry. If the Lord and Maſter was called an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> no wonder if thoſe of his houſhold be called ſo. Our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity will not ſecure us from infamy. The choiceſt of Profeſſors have had black marks in the worlds Kalender. It is uſuall for thoſe who live in treaſon and rebellion againſt the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to ſlander his ſervants with trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and rebellion againſt the Kings of the Earth.</p>
            <p>But, my dear Brethren, take heed of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99213:13"/>this; for as the death of the Saints is precious, ſo the names of the Saints are precious in Gods account. The world will father a hundred Lyes upon the Lords people. <hi>Men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſely for my ſake,</hi> Math. 5.11. 2 Tim. 2.9. Wicked men hate them moſt, that God loves moſt; But God will roul away the reproaches of his people; he will cauſe their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and righteouſneſs to break forth as the Sun at noon day; and their names ſhall be in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: Yea, at that great day God will clear their innocency before men and Angels, and all the world.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Ninthly, Keep in with God, now men are out with you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it is good for me to draw near to God: I have put my truſt in the Lord God that I may declare all thy works,</hi> Pſal. 73.28. He that dwelleth under the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the moſt High, no plague ſhall come nigh him: <hi>He will give his Angels charge over thee,</hi> Pſal. 91.10. <hi>Though the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99213:13"/>Fig-tree ſhould not bloſſome, and there be no fruit in the Vine, though the labour of the Olive ſhould faile, and the fields ſhould yield no meat, the flock ſhould be cut off from the fold, and the herd from the ſtalls: Yet I will rejoyce in the Lord, I will tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the God of my ſalvation,</hi> Hab. 3.17.18. <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, and the righteous runneth into it, and are ſafe,</hi> James 4.8. <hi>Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you.</hi> This is a great comfort to the people of <hi>God;</hi> though they be as Lillies amongſt Thorns, and as ſheep amongſt Wolves; that they have a <hi>God</hi> to go to. <hi>Come my people, enter into thy Chambers, &amp; ſhut thy doors about thee; hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, until the indignation be overpaſt,</hi> Iſa. 26.20. Let the world frown, and friends forſake you, God can ſweeten all your enjoyments, keep in Gods way, and you will be ſure of Gods protection: doe you keep Gods precepts, and God will keep your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: do what God commands, and avoid what God forbids, and then you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99213:14"/>need not fear what men can doe unto you. If you would have God to take care of you, you muſt caſt your care upon God: wait on him, and walk with him; obey his precepts, and believe his promiſes.</p>
            <p>Oh beloved, Let wicked men fall out with us, and hate us, and reproach us, and puniſh us as much as they will, if we keep in with God: therefore, my beloved, above all things get commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, and keep communion with God: Communion with God will yield you two Heavens; a Heaven upon Earth, and a Heaven after death; all Saints ſhall enjoy a Heaven when they leave the Earth; ſome Saints en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a Heaven whileſt they are on the Earth. He enjoyes nothing that wants communion with God; he wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothing that enjoyes communion with God.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Tenthly, Live above the love of Life, and the fear of death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For whoſoever will ſave his Life, ſhall loſe it; and whoſoever will loſe his life for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99213:14"/>my ſake ſhall find it,</hi> Matth. 16.25. <hi>If any man come unto me, and hate not his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, and wife, and children, and brethren, and ſiſters, yea, and his own life alſo, he cannot be my Diſciple,</hi> Luke, 14.16. He that loves not Chriſt more than his life, will be ſure to ſave and to keep both. He that goes out of Gods way to avoid danger, ſhall certainly meet with danger, <hi>Ye are not your own, for ye are bought with a price: therefore glorifie God in your body, and in your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which are Gods,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.19, 20.</p>
            <p>My dear friends, Let us live above ſuffering and fears, though we cannot live without ſuffering: <hi>In the world you ſhall have tribulation; but be of good cheer, I have overcome the world.</hi> I have overcome the world for you, and I have overcome the world in you, <hi>John</hi> 16.33. He that loves Chriſt above his life, will let life go rather then Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Conſider my beloved, Chriſt and the cloud of Witneſſes and Martyrs that are gone before, and are paſſed over and through all thoſe floods, and ſafely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99213:15"/>arived to ſhoar, and are now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with God, and Chriſt, and holy Angels, where there is fulneſs of joy, and pleaſures for evermore. <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of Life; in thy preſence is fulneſſe of joy, and at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore, Pſal.</hi> 16.11. Oh the joy, that they enjoy! Oh the rivers of conſolations, that flowes from God! <hi>Therefore are they before the throne of God, and ſerve him day and night in his temple: and he that ſitteth on the throne ſhall dwell amongſt them. They ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sun light on them, nor any heat; for the Lamb which is in the midſt of the throne, ſhall feed them, &amp; ſhal lead them into living fountains of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes,</hi> Rev. 7.15, 16, 17. Who are they that have all this honour, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and joy, and bleſſedneſs in Heaven. For this ſee verſe 14. <hi>Theſe are they which came out of great tribulation, and have waſhed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.</hi> The ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99213:15"/>of the Crown which Believers ſhall receive, will make them amends for the bitterneſſe of the Croſſe they carried.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Eleventhly, Deſire better hearts, more then better times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Jeruſalem, waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaved: how long ſhall thy vaine thoughts lodge within thee?</hi> Jer. 4.14. <hi>For out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, falſewitneſs, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> Mat. 15.19: <hi>The heart is deceitful above all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi> Jer. 17.9.</p>
            <p>Oh Beloved, inſtead of reforming, we are complaining of wicked men, more then of wickedneſs; of their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, more than our Apoſtacy; of their injuries againſt us, than our injuries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. We pore too much upon ſecond cauſes, or complaine of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not of our ſelves. We have been a long time in ſinning, and we had need be a long time in repenting: the times had not been ſo bad, had not we been
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99213:16"/>ſo bad; and the times would ſoon be better, if we were but better.</p>
            <p>Alas, Beloved, we have ſinned ſuch ſins as unrighteous men could not ſin; againſt the cleareſt Light, and deareſt Love: the better God hath been to us, the worſe we have been to him: he hath loaded us with his mercies, and we have wearied him with our ſinnes: Oh let us blame our ſelves more, and the times leſſe: Let us turne unto the Lord, that he may turne to us in love and mercy: Let our hearts go out to him, that his heart may come unto us. Oh beg and cry for better hearts, that you may ſerve God better: for broken hearts, for ſincere hearts; for that is that God looks at, and calls for, Prov. 23.26. <hi>My Son, give me thy heart;</hi> Our hearts are alwayes out of tune to ſerve God; but never out of tune to ſerve ſin: for if we had never ſo good times, and not good hearts, it would rather hurts us than bleſſe us.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Twelfthly, Grow downward in humility, and inward in ſincerity.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99213:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto me, who am leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints, is this grace given that I ſhould preach among the Gentiles the unſearcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble riches of Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 3.8. <hi>And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall exalt himſelf, ſhall be abaſed; and he that ſhall humble himſelf, ſhall be exalted,</hi> Mat, 23.12. <hi>Put on therefore (as the Elect of God holy and beloved) bowels of mercy, kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of mind, meekneſſe, long-fuſtering,</hi> Col. 3.12. <hi>Be cloathed with humility; for God reſiſteth the proud, and giveth grace to the humble; Humble your ſelves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.5, 6. Bring up your will to God, that God may bring down his will to you. Be low in your own eyes; keep a low eſteem of your ſelves; abhor pride, and flye from it; be inwardly ſincere, as well as out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly humble. Do not look Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by your profeſſion, and Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by your converſation: He that lives in ſin, is dead in ſin, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity,</hi> Epheſ. 6.24. Let
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99213:17"/>your hearts be upright with <hi>God,</hi> and walk as thoſe that have <hi>God</hi> for their portion; Knowing there are many eies upon you; the eye of <hi>God,</hi> the eye of Chriſt, the eye of Angels, the eye of Saints, the eye of the world, and the Divell eyes you too; therefore walk wiſely and ſincerely; be like the Kings Daughter all glorious within, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.3. <hi>She is all glorious within,</hi> though within is not all her glory, <hi>Her cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is of wrought gold;</hi> Doe not think your ſelves good becauſe others think ſo: Alas, the beſt mens confidences of us are poor Evidences for Heaven: the beſt Teſtimony is that within us, and above us. See therefore that ye grow in grace, and delight in holineſs; bring forth much fruit; live ſtill as before the living <hi>God;</hi> take heed of Hypocriſie and Apoſtacy; make it your daily bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to walk with <hi>God;</hi> be much in the exerciſe of humility: Humility will exceedingly adorn your profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Doe not place Religion in a few good words, when the ſubſtance is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99213:17"/>but live as you would die; live to day as if you were to dye to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Thirteenthly, Doe good to thoſe that be good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah 6.8. <hi>That they do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.18. <hi>But do good, and to communicate forget not; for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed,</hi> Heb. 13.16. <hi>Pure religion, and undefiled before God and the Father, is this, to viſit the fatherleſſe, and widdows in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,</hi> James 1.27. Forget not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the neceſſities of the poor Saints, think that <hi>God</hi> hath given you your Eſtates, for ſuch a time as this.</p>
            <p>Oh Beloved, what an opportunity have you now to do good if Satan do not hinder you? are there not many of Chriſts Miniſters now in want, and Members in want? ſome in priſon, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99213:18"/>others out of priſon: <hi>Remember thoſe that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them that ſuffer adverſity, as being your ſelves alſo in the body,</hi> Heb. 13.3. There be many men that have a great deal of this worlds wealth, and riches, and goods in their hands, and in their houſes; but they have no grace in their hearts; and therefore they do no good with the goods of this world: they live ſo unfruitfull, that their lives are ſcarce worth a prayer, not their deaths ſcarce worth a tear. Men may as well go to Hell for not doing good, as for doing evil: he that bears not good fruit is as well fuel for Hell, as he that bears bad. You may not be outwardly bad, and yet not inwardly good; you may be as far from grace, as from vice: Men are not ſo much ſent to Hell for doing evil, as for not doing good: <hi>For I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat: I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink,</hi> Math. 25.42. The rich glutton was in Hell torments, not for perſecuting <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> but not relieving <hi>Lazarus. Meroz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99213:18"/>was curſed by the Angel, not becauſe they fought againſt the Lord, but <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they came not to help the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> Judges 5.23. It is one of the greateſt mercies in the world, for <hi>God</hi> to give a man a heart to doe good with that he hath given him.</p>
            <p>Oh Beloved, be always a doing good and hating evil: Look not only where you may get good, but where you may do good: Labour to be helpful to the ſouls of others, and to ſupply the wants of others.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Fourteenthly, Chuſe chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before defilement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes, when he was come to years, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to be called the Sonne of Pharaohs daughter, chuſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon,</hi> Heb. 11.24.25. <hi>For ye had compaſſion of me in my bonds, and took joyfully the ſpoiling of your goods knowing in your ſelves that ye have in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a better, and an enduring ſubſtance,</hi> Heb. 10.34. So the three Children
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99213:19"/>choſe burning in the fiery furnace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bowing to the Golden Image, <hi>Daniel</hi> 3.17.18. <hi>We are not careful to anſwer thee in this matter. If it be ſo, our God whom we ſerve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and he will deliver us out of thy hand O King. But if not, be it known unto thee O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image that thou haſt ſet up.</hi> So <hi>Daniel</hi> choſe ſuffering before ſinning: And it is ſaid of thoſe in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. they accepted not of deliverance; <hi>and others were tortured, not accepting delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that they might obtaine a better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Beloved, there is more evill in the leaſt ſin againſt Chriſt, than in the greateſt ſuffering for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Our ſufferings for Chriſt are but light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, But ſhort, but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt ſtands by us in out ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Our ſufferings are ordered by the Father.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99213:19"/>
            <p>Fifthly, Our ſufferings ſhall not hurt our ſouls:</p>
            <p>Sixthly, God gives us the beſt of comforts in the worſt of times: we have moſt of conſolations from God, when we have moſt of tribulations from men: as our ſufferings do abound, ſo our conſolations do abound: When the burden is heavieſt upon the back, when the peace of conſcience is ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and greateſt within. Therefore my dear brethren, keep your ſelves out of the puddle of this world, and from the evil of this world; and if you muſt ſin or ſuffer, chuſe ſuffering before ſinning.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. Fifteenthly, Think not the worſe of godlineſs becauſe it is frown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon; nor the better of ungodlineſs becauſe it is ſmiled upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For bodily exerciſe profiteth little, but Godlineſſe is profitable unto all things, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.8. <hi>Yea, doubtleſſe, and I count all things but loſſe, for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord; for whom I have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99213:20"/>ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and do count them but dung that I may win Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.8. <hi>And have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them,</hi> Epheſ. 5.11. <hi>For the wages of ſin is death, but the gift of God is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Rom. 6.23.</p>
            <p>Oh Friends, think not the worſe of holineſſe, becauſe it is reproached and ſcorned, and perſecuted by wicked men and Divels; nor the better of wickedneſſe, becauſe wicked men love it, and follow it, and ſay, <hi>It is in vain to ſerve God; and what profit is it that we have kept his Ordinances, and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord of Hoſts</hi> Mal. 3.14. But there is a time coming, when ungodly men would be glad of ſome of that holineſſe that now they deſpiſe; but they ſhall be as far then from obtaining it, as they are now from deſiring it. Let us therfore love holineſs and hate wickedneſſe; <hi>For without holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs no man ſhal ſee the Lord,</hi> Heb. 12.14.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99213:20"/>Holineſſe is the only way to happineſs. We muſt not dreſſe our ſelves for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, by the Looking-glaſſe of this world: <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to do evil,</hi> Exod. 23.2. <hi>For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the Groſſe of Chriſt; whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe god is their belly, and whoſe glory is in their ſhame, who mind earthly things,</hi> Phil. 3.18.19. The Children of God muſt be harmleſſe in their actings, and blameleſſe in their walkings.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. Sixteenthly, Prize the Word of God by the worth of it, that you may never come to prize the Word of God by the want of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How ſweet are thy words unto my taſt! Yea, ſweeter than honey to my mouth,</hi> Pſal. 119:10. <hi>It is ſweeter than the honey and the honey-comb,</hi> Pſal. 19.10. <hi>Oh how do I Love thy Law!</hi> Pſal. 119.97. I love thy Commandements above Gold; yea, above fine Gold. <hi>The Law of thy mouth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99213:21"/>is better to me than thouſands of Gold and Silver,</hi> Verſe 72. <hi>As new born babes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the ſincere milk of the Word, that they may grow thereby,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.2. <hi>Let the Word of God dwell richly in you;</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you, but in you, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. Oh let us with <hi>Job</hi> eſteeme the Word of God above our neceſſary food, <hi>Job</hi> 23.12. and with <hi>David</hi> above our Gold and Silver. The delight of a Saint in Gods Word, over-tops all his creature delights. Wicked men can delight in the Creatures of God, but not in the Word of God; they can delight in the gifts of God, but not in the God of gifts. Oh let us love the word, and prize the word: it is the Sun of the Chriſtian world. As the Sun is the light of the naturall world, and without it the world is but a Chaos, and a dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on full of darkneſs; ſo is the Word of God the light of the Spiritual world, without which a Chriſtian is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal night. Take away the Scriptures, and there will be no certain rule to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect men what is to be done, or what is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99213:21"/>to be believed: All falſe wayes are here diſcovered, all ſins are here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, all holineſs is here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Here you may ſee every action and motion of your Lives, as a ſtep to Life, or a ſtep to Death; as a ſtep Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-ward, or a ſtep Hell-ward; Oh therefore prize the word, and obey the Word.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a plain Word.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is a perfect Word,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is a ſure Word.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is an uniform Word.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is a powerful Word; it is the ſavour of life unto life, unto them that believe:</p>
            <p>Oh Beloved, let us read the Word, and abide in the Word: <hi>If ye continue in my Word, then are ye my Diſciples,</hi> Joh. 8.31: The leſſe now you hear, the more doe you read, that little Book of the <hi>Revelations</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Seventeenthly, have a care of the Whore of <hi>Babylons</hi> golden Cup and ſweet Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Woman was arrayed in purple,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99213:22"/>and ſcarlet colour, and decked with Gold and precious ſtones, and pearls; having a golden Cup in her hand ſull of abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and filthineſſe of her fornication,</hi> Rev. 17.4. <hi>And the Serpent caſt out of his mouth water, as a flood after the Woman, that he might cauſe her to be carried away of the flood,</hi> Rev. 12.15. Let me beſeech you to have a care of this, and keep your ſelves from this: Be like the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Spouſe of Chriſt, which followeth him whereſoever he goeth.</p>
            <p>My Dear Friends, keep your ſelves from four things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From falſe Teachers. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hath his Miniſters as well as Chriſt. <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets, which come to you in Sheeps cloathing, but inwardly they are ravening Wolves,</hi> Math. 7.15. <hi>Yea, they are greedy Doggs, which can never have enough, and they are Shepherds that cannot underſtand: they all look to their own way, every own for his gain from his quarter,</hi> Iſa. 56.11. Oh falſe Teachers do not feed the Flock, but fleece the Flock; they do not convert; but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99213:22"/>they do not ſeaſon, but poiſon; they do not edifie to ſalvation, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie to damnation; inſtead of curing ſouls, they kill ſouls; ſo they have but the peoples goods, they care not though the Devil have their ſoules; they are neither rightly called, nor rightly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, nor rightly ordained; <hi>Their courſe is evil, and therefore is not right,</hi> Jer. 13.10. They are like Doggs and Wolves combining together to mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Flock of Chriſt. Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore keep your ſelves from <hi>Babylons</hi> Merchants, that make Merchandize of the ſouls of men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.13. Oh, the ſins of the Teachers, are the Teachers of ſins.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From falſe Doctrine. <hi>But there were falſe Prophets alſo among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1. <hi>Be not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with divers and ſtrange Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; for it is a good thing that the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99213:23"/>heart be eſtabliſhed with grace, not with meats; which have not profited them that have been occupied therein,</hi> Hebrews 13.9.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you alſo in the Lord, my Dear Brethren, that you doe not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally comply with, nor ſuperſtitiouſly conform to the Inventions of men: But <hi>ſtand faſt in the Liberty, wherewith Chriſt hath made you free,</hi> Gal. 5.1.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, From falſe Worſhip. <hi>If any man Worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and receive his mark in his forehead, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture into the Cup of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and he ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 14.9, 10. <hi>Ye Worſhip ye know not what. God is a Spirit, and they that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit, and in Iruth,</hi> Joh. 4.23, 24. As there be ſome in the World that worſhip falſe Gods, ſo there be others that Worſhip the true God with falſe Worſhip. They
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99213:23"/>that worſhip the Beaſt, worſhip the Devil, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. Oh meddle not with falſe worſhip, with vain worſhip, and will-worſhip: worſhip God as he teacheth us to worſhip him. Our work is to depend on Chriſts work: our outward working depends on Gods inward working.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, From falſe Opinions, from Errour and Sedition: Let your hearts be upright, your judgements ſound, and your lives holy: Love the Truth, obey the Truth, and hold faſt the Truth.</p>
            <p>Now Beloved, Let me beſeech you for Gods ſake, and for Chriſts ſake, and for your Soules ſake, keep your ſelves from falſe Teachers, from falſe Doctrine, from falſe worſhip, from falſe Opinions. If you will be taſting and ſiping at <hi>Babylons</hi> cup, you muſt reſolve to receive more or leſſe of <hi>Babylons</hi> plagues.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. Eighteenthly, Be one with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that is one with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Endeavouring to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99213:24"/>Spirit in the bond of peace. There is one body, and one Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your Calling: One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all,</hi> Epheſ. 4.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Every one that loveth him that begat, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him alſo that is begotten of him. By this we know that we love the Children of God, when we love God and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.1, 2. <hi>He that loveth not his Brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> 1 John 4.26.</p>
            <p>Oh Conſider what a diſhonour it is to the Goſpel, that thoſe that profeſſe themſelves Sonnes of the ſame God, Members of the ſame Chriſt, Temples of the ſame Spirit, Heirs of the ſame Glory, ſhould be at a jarring one with another. It is ſtrange and unnaturall, that Lillies ſhould prove thorns to one another! that thoſe who are Saints in profeſſion, ſhould be Devils in practiſe to one another! that Gods Diamonds ſhould cut one another! For Wolves
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99213:24"/>to devour the Lambs is no wonder, but for one Lamb to devour another is a wonder, and monſtrous! Oh, that Chriſtians inſtead of loving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould hate one another! Oh how unlike are we to that God whom we profeſſe to be our God! He is full of love, full of goodneſs, and full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and patience: Oh but Chriſtians cannot beare, and forbear one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Oh do not wicked men warm themſelves at the ſparks of our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſay it is as we would have it?</p>
            <p>Oh Beloved, hath not God made his wrath to ſmoke againſt us for the diviſions and heart-burnings that have been amongſt us? Oh that you would lay this to heart, and throw away all diſcord and diviſions, and heart burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and labour for a oneneſſe in love and affection, with every one that is one with Chriſt. Oh labour for a healing ſpirit. You cannot love God if you do not love the people of God. <hi>If any man ſaith he loveth God, and hateth his brother, he is a lyer. Let brotherly love
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99213:25"/>continue,</hi> Heb. 13.1. <hi>They that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another,</hi> Mal. 3.16. Chriſts Doves ſhould flock toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There be many that cannot love a man, unleſſe he be of their Opinion, or a Member of their Church, though he be a Member of Chriſt. Every man hath a good opinion of his own opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But alas Beloved, it is not this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, or that opinion; this way, or that way, will bring a man to Heaven without faith in Chriſt; and he that hath faith in Chriſt, hath a right to all the Ordinances of Chriſt, and Promiſes of Chriſt, and Priviledges of Chriſt; therefore let me beſeech you to love every man that is a godly man, let him be of what way and form he will. <hi>And the multitude of them that believed, were of one heart, and of one ſoul,</hi> Acts 4.38.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. Nineteenthly, Love Chriſt with a Love ſtronger then life, who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us with a love ſtronger than death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doth my father love me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I lay down my life, that I might take
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99213:25"/>it again: no man taketh it from me, but I lay it down my ſelf. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again,</hi> John 10.17, 18. <hi>This is a faithful ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and worthy of all acceptation, That Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. Chriſts love to us was ſtronger then death; he dyed for love; he laid down his life to ſave our lives; he loves us as the Father loves him, <hi>John</hi> 15.9. <hi>As the Father hath loved me, ſo have I loved you: continue ye in my love.</hi> Oh the Scripture hath exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing high expreſſions of his affection to us. Now Beloved, if he died for us, and ſuffered for us, and ſet his heart upon us to love us, and delight in us; how ought we then to love him again! <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind,</hi> Math. 22.37, 38. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, and there is none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth that I deſire beſides thee,</hi> Pſal. 73.25. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you therefore which believe he is precious,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.7. Oh let our hearts be full of love and affections to Chriſt.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99213:26"/>Love will breed courage, and caſt out fear, ſlaviſh fear before God, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal fear before men: God can keep us from the torments of men, but men cannot keep us from the torments of God. Whileſt we ſtand by God, God hath promiſed to ſtand by us: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not afraid of any Authority that ſtands in oppoſition to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Chriſt. None can promiſe us better than Chriſt can; none can threaten us worſe than Chriſt can? Can any man promiſe us with better then Heaven? Can any man threaten us with worſe than Hell? Heaven is promiſed to thoſe that love him; and Hell is to be the portion of thoſe that hate him.</p>
            <p>Oh my dear Brethren, Let us Love Chriſt with a love ſtronger then death: ſo did <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, or diſtreſſe, or perſecution or famine, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or ſword?</hi> Rom. 8.35. Love is ſtronger than Death; many waters
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99213:26"/>cannot quench it, neither can the floods drown it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.6, 7.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. Twentiethly, Be every day as ſerious in your preparation for death, as if it were your laſt day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time will I wait till my change come,</hi> Job 14.14. <hi>This night thy ſoule ſhall be required of thee,</hi> Luke 12.20. <hi>For what is your life? it is even a vapour that appeareth a little time, and then vaniſheth away,</hi> Jam. 4.14. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thou haſt made my days as an hand-breadth, and mine age is as nothing before thee: Verily, every man at his beſt ſtate is altogether vanity,</hi> Pſal. 39.5. As no Saint knows when that time and hour ſhall be; ſo no wicked man knows when it ſhall not be. To live without fear of death, is to dye living: To labour not to dye is labour in vain. Men are afraid to dye in ſuch and ſuch ſins, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to live in ſuch and ſuch ſins. Oh the Hell of horrors and terrors that attend thoſe ſoules that have their greateſt work to do when they come to dye! therefore as you would be happy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99213:27"/>in death, and everlaſtingly bleſſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, prepare and fit your ſelves for death. Did Chriſt dye for us that we might live with him, and ſhall not we deſire to dye and be with him? A Believers dying day is his Crowning day. <hi>And I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying, unto me, write, bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them,</hi> Rev. 14.13.</p>
            <p>Oh I beſeech you my dear Brethren, every day ſpend ſome time in prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for, and meditation of Death, Judgement, Hell, Heaven, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Eternity is a ſum that can never be numbred, a line that can never be meaſured: Eternity is a condition of everlaſting ſorrow, or everlaſting joy. Oh think of this, and prepare for this every day before the night of death comes.</p>
            <p>And thus my beloved, I have given you theſe Twenty precious directions for your ſouls.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99213:27"/>
            <p>I ſhall leave this Book with you as a Legacy of my deareſt Love: my deſire in all this, is your happineſs here, and your bleſſedneſs hereafter. My earneſt and humble deſire of you is, That you would mind this Book and my former Treatiſe; not only read them, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your lives by them. O do your Duty, love your Duty, and live your Duty, that you may be made meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light; Which is, and ſhall be the earneſt and conſtant Prayer of one that eſteems it a moſt glorious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be of the number of thoſe who follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Dyer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99213:28"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. 14.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Theſe are they which follow the Lamb whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever he goeth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Title of this Book tells us, it is <hi>The Revelation of John,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> tells us Chap. 1.1. it is <hi>the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation to <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>John</hi>'s Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to us.</p>
            <p>The Comma of this Book is ſet forth Chap. 1.19. <hi>VVrite the things that are, and the things that ſhall be hereafter,</hi> And into theſe two parts this book is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a Relation of the things that are, referring to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, A Revelation of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtate of the Church to come, and that from <hi>John</hi>'s time unto the ſecond coming of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The words of this Book are the true ſayings of the true God, they are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>true and faithful,</hi> Chap. 22.6.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99213:28"/>
            <p>The matter of this Book ſo much concerns the good of the Church, that Jeſus Chriſt commandeth every one that hath an ear to heare, to hearken what the Spirit of God ſaith unto the Church: and to ſhew how earneſt Chriſt Jeſus is to have all his Members and Servants acquainted with the things revealed in this <hi>Book,</hi> this charge he repeated eight times over, as this Book ſhewes, Chap. 2.7, 11, 17, 29. And Chap. 3.6, 13, 22. And Chap. 13.9.</p>
            <p>A bleſſing is pronounced upon the Reader, Hearer, and Doer of the things written in this Book <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.3. O what can be ſaid more, or more effectually to ſtir us up to hear and read, than bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs? <hi>And bleſſed is he that keepeth the words of the Propheſie of this Book, Chap.</hi> 22.7. But how ſhall we keep them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we know them? and how ſhall we know them, except we read them?</p>
            <p>The excellency of this Book is ſuch, as neither Man nor Angel, none in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Earth, or under the Earth, was found worthy ſo much as to look into
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99213:29"/>it, till Jeſus Chriſt went &amp; took out of his Fathers hand to open it unto us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p>The bleſſed St. <hi>John</hi> could not but weep for fear leaſt this book ſhould have been kept cloſe from him and the Church; ſo earneſt was he to know thoſe things, which we neglect to know <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>This book is a moſt precious Jewel, which Chriſt hath beſtowed upon his Church in the latter dayes; and it is our great duty to look into it, and read it, ſtudy it, open it, and expound it, that all the people may thorowly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it, eſpecially in theſe times; for now in this Age is and ſhall be the very heat of the war and brunt of the battle betwixt God and Beliall, betwixt Chriſt and Antichriſt, betwixt the Lambs followers and the Beaſts followers. Now this book lyeth all open, and plainly telleth us what ſhall be the iſſue and ſucceſſe in the day of battel; which ſide ſhall have the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and which ſide ſhall go down, <hi>Chap.</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99213:29"/>17.19. And certainly the ſons of Belial ſhall not long prevail; the date of their Reigne is almoſt out, and the time draweth on apace wherein both they and their <hi>Beaſt</hi> ſhall be laid in the duſt.</p>
            <p>This book ſheweth us the riſing of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> the declining of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the ruine of the <hi>Beaſt, Chap.</hi> 18:</p>
            <p>Our Lord Jeſus hath ſhewed us in this book the ſorrowes, and ſufferings, and afflictions, and tribulations, which the Church was to meet withal in the latter times, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.7. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.14, 15. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.7.</p>
            <p>And her deadly and cruel Enemies; the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Mother of Harlots, the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> the falſe Prophet, and the great red Dragon which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth War againſt her, and caſteth out floods after her, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12:17:</p>
            <p>This book ſheweth us likewiſe the true State of the true Church upon Earth; what ſhe is, where ſhe is, how ſhe is, and what ſhe ſhall be hereafter; and that before the ſlaying, under the ſlaying, and after the ſlaying.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99213:30"/>
            <p n="1">1. Before the ſlaying time the true Church is in the Wilderneſs, <hi>where ſhe hath a place prepared her of God, that they ſhould feed her there a thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore dayes, Chap.</hi> 12.2. Before the ſlaying of the Witneſſes the true Worſhippers of God are in a low condition, in heavineſſe and ſadneſſe, in ſack-cloth and aſhes, in a mourning and ſuffering State; being ſcattered and diſperſed here and there, as <hi>Iſraell</hi> was of old. But though this be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the poor Woman in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, yet ſhe is not without comfort; ſhe may take comfort in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>God</hi> prepared a place for her.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>God</hi> nouriſhed her, &amp; locked her up in his chamber of Providence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That God numbered her dayes of ſuffering: The Tribulation of the Saints of the Old Teſtament is recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up ſtill by years; as the bondage of <hi>Egypt</hi> four hundred and thirty years; and the Captivity of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſeventy years: But under the New Teſtament by Dayes; <hi>Ye ſhall have tribulation ten
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99213:30"/>dayes, Chap.</hi> 2.10. <hi>And the two witneſſes ſhall lye dead three dayes and a half, Chap: Chap.</hi> 11.9. So the Woman was to be in the wilderneſs a thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore days.</p>
            <p>The Church is compared to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for four Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As as woman is weak and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo is the Church, and can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 15.5.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As a woman is uſeful and fruitful, ſo is the Church, <hi>John</hi> 15.2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As a woman is faire and beautiful, ſo is the Church, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.13.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As a woman is full of love &amp; affection, ſo is the Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2: Under the ſlaying time the true worſhippers of God and witneſſes of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>lie dead in the Street of the great City, which is ſpiritually called</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>and</hi> Egypt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.8: That is, in Antichriſts Kingdoms and Dominions. <hi>The Woman which thou ſaweſt, is that great City, which reigneth over the Kings of the Earth, Chap.</hi> 17.18.</p>
            <p>She is called <hi>Sodom</hi> for her filthineſs
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99213:31"/>and wickedneſs, and <hi>Egypt</hi> for her cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and oppreſſion, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.4.</p>
            <p>The true Servants of God and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Jeſus Chriſt, that bear witneſſe for him againſt the evils of the Beaſt, and againſt the evils of the world, are here called <hi>two</hi> witneſſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe of the fewneſſe of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe two is a number ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to bear a witneſs, <hi>John</hi> 8.17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe Antichriſts <hi>Beaſts</hi> are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led two, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are called witneſſes for Six Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe their work is to bear witneſs for Chriſt and his truth, againſt the world, the Fleſh and the Devill. A true believer is to bear a threefold teſtimony to and for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> a word-teſtimony to and for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> a word-teſtimony, a life-teſtimony, and a blood teſtimony, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>John</hi> 5.33.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Chriſts</hi> Members are called witneſſes, becauſe they ſtand up for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to maintaine his name, his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, his cauſe, his truth, his worſhip, his Glory in the world, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16, 17, 18,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99213:31"/>and <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>And ye killed the Prince of life, whom God hath raiſed from the dead, whereof we are witneſſes,</hi> Act. 3.15. <hi>Be it known unto you all, and to all the people of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that by the name of Jeſus Chriſt of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>whom ye crucified, whom God raiſed from the dead, even by him doth this man ſtand here before you whole,</hi> Acts 4.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Lambs followers are called witneſſes, becauſe they keep the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.17: <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.9. a teſtimony to all the Offices, works, and Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, as <hi>King of Saints,</hi> and <hi>King of Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Gods choſen and precious ones are called witneſſes, becauſe they doe appear boldly and openly for his truth; they own it, they love it, they love it, they publiſh it, they hold it faſt, and ſuffer for it, who through the teachings of the Spirit in the word, and by the power of the ſame ſpirit are found in the practiſe of Chriſts Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments: they cannot deny the truth, which is a Teſtimony to it, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99213:32"/>
            <p>Fifthly, The true VVorſhippers of God are called witneſſes, becauſe they do bear witneſs againſt the beaſt, and all the whole miſtery of iniquity; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who hath committed fornication with the Kings of the earth, <hi>and made her ſelf drunk with the blood of the Saints,</hi> Rev. 17.6. <hi>Chriſts,</hi> faithful witneſſes bear an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Teſtimony againſt all her abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and filthineſs and wickedneſs, againſt the Pope, his Government, his clergy, his Doctrine, his worſhip, his Religion, and all his abominable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Chriſts</hi> redeemed ones are called witneſſes, becauſe in dying they bear witneſſe for him; for to dye for the truth is a living ſtanding teſtimony to it. He who for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake loves not his life unto the death, dyes a moſt glorious witneſſe of Chriſt; <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.11. <hi>And they loved not their lives unto the death. And the beaſt that came out of the bottomleſſe pit made war againſt him, and overcame them, and killed them, Chap.</hi> 11.7.9.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:99213:32"/>
            <p>Antichriſt riſeth in a double beaſt; In his civil power; and his Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal power.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In his civil power; ſo he makes up one beaſt with the ten Kings, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.12. <hi>And this is that Beaſt that riſe up out of the Sea, which hath ſeven heads and ten horns, and upon his horns ten Crowns, and upon his heads the name of blaſphemy. And the beaſt which I ſaw was like unto a Leaper, and his feet was as the feet of a Bear, and his mouth as the mouth of a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the Dragon gave him his Power, and his Seat, and great Authority, Chap.</hi> 13.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In his Eccleſiaſticall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; ſo he makes up another beaſt with the Clergy: and this is that beaſt that riſe up out of the Earth; <hi>He hath two horns like a Lamb, and he ſpeaks like a Dragon,</hi> verſ. 11.</p>
            <p>Now theſe two monſtrous beaſts (Antichriſts Magiſtrates and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) ſlay the faithful witneſſes of Jeſus Chriſt, and rejoyce over their dead bodies, and make merry, and ſend gifts
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99213:33"/>one to another, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.10. Oh how do graceleſs, faithleſs, Chriſtleſs men rejoyce at the afflictions and calamities of Gods people! ſaying, where is now your God, and Chriſt your King? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.10.</p>
            <p>As touching the nature of the VVit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes death, we are not to conceive thereof as though the ſame were to be a corporeall killing or ſlaying; but a civill killing or ſlaying, not ſo much their bodies as their teſtimonies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive and ſtrip them of their Liberty, Worſhip, Ordinances, Religion, and the free exerciſe of their Gifts, ſuffering not a Servant of Jeſus Chriſts to bear an open teſtimony againſt the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the beaſt, nor againſt their National wickedneſs; but make Laws againſt them, and lye in wait for them, ſtoping their mouths, and impriſoning their bodies, hating and hunting them up and down, afflicting and torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and taking poſſeſſion of their poſſeſſions: <hi>Killing and ſlaying them all the day long, and account them as ſheep
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99213:33"/>for the ſlaughter,</hi> Rom. 8.33. This is to be <hi>broken in the place of Dragons, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the ſhadow of death,</hi> Pſal. 44.19. This is to be killed all the day long: And upon this account, the witneſſes are ſaid to be ſlain, <hi>And after three days and an half, the Spirit of life from God entred into them; and they ſtood upon their feet, and great fear fell upon them that ſaw them, Chap.</hi> 11.11. A ſpirit of boldneſſe and courage, zeale and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedneſſe and reſolution to appear for Chriſt and his cauſe, againſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and the whole brood. Therefore rejoyce all ye Saints, and be glad all ye of upright heart; though the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be dead, they will not alwayes be dead, but riſe again.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After the ſlaying time the true Church is with the Lamb on Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> Chap. 14.1. <hi>And I looked, and lo, a Lamb ſtood on Mount Sion, and with him an hundred forty and four thouſand, having his fathers name written in their foreheads:</hi> which notes a fixed ſtate: <hi>Thoſe which truſt in the Lord ſhall be as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99213:34"/>Mount Sion, which cannot be moved,</hi> Pſal. 12.5. before the ſlaying time the Church is very low, but under the ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time lower, but after the ſlaying time the Church is very high, ſhe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, ſhining, and triumphing on Mount <hi>Sion: And they ſung as it were a new ſong before the throne, and before the four beaſts, and the Elders, and no man could learn that ſong but the hundred forty and four thouſand which were redeemed from the Earth.</hi> The true Church ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gotten the glorious preſence of the Lamb in the midſt of her, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gotten ſome victory over the <hi>beaſt</hi> they do rejoyce mightily. <hi>And I heard a voice of Harpers, harping with their Harps:</hi> but this is not till after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the witneſſes are riſen, the Church is exceeding joyful.</p>
            <p>This chapter out of which my Text is taken containeth ſix principal things</p>
            <p>Firſt, A Lovely Deſcription of Jeſus Chriſt; and he is deſcribed by the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of a Lamb: Lo, <hi>a Lamb ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mount Sion,</hi> verſ. 1. And <hi>behold the Lamb of God,</hi> Joh. 1.19.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99213:34"/>
            <p>He is called a Lamb in a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of his innocency, 1 Pet. 1.19.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In reſpect of his meekneſs and patience, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.32.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A Lively Deſcription of the Church, the Lambs wife, and that from verſ. 1. to verſ. 5.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A glorious Deſcription of the Churches Miniſters. As the Church is in this book called Heaven, ſo her Miniſters are called Angels: <hi>And I ſaw another Angel flying in the midſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, having the everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> ver. 6. <hi>And there followed another Angel, ſaying, Babylon is fallen,</hi> verſ. 8. <hi>And the third Angell followed him, ſaying with a loud voyce,</hi> &amp;c. Verſ. 9.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Here is ſet down the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which theſe Angels preach and publiſh.</p>
            <p>The firſt Angell publiſhed the free Grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the inventions of men: <hi>Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a loud voice, fear God, and give
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99213:35"/>Glory to him, and worſhip him that made Heaven and Earth, and the Sea and the Fountains of waters,</hi> verſ. 7. Namely, That men ſhould once fear God, and worſhip him, and give all glory to him; none to Creatures, none to Images, none to Antichriſt; he that worſhipeth the Beaſt, worſhipeth the Dragon and the Divel, Chap. 13.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Angell proclaimed the utter ruine of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction thereof, over the world, <hi>ſaying, Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great City, becauſe ſhe hath made all Nations drink of the wive of the wrath of her fornication,</hi> verſ. 8.</p>
            <p>The third Angel doth ſeriouſly and ſolemnly give warning to all thoſe who ſhall yet adhere to the Beaſt, ſhewing the danger and miſery of it. <hi>If any man worſhip the heaſt and his Image, and receive his mark in his forehead, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture into the Cup of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and he ſhall be tormented with fire
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99213:35"/>and brimſtone, in the preſence of the Holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb,</hi> verſ. 19.20.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, A ſweet word of heavenly conſolation to the Saints and People of God; <hi>And I heard a voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaying unto me, write, bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord; from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth they reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them,</hi> verſ. 13.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The Judgments and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which ſhall be executed upon the falſe Church: the Spirit doth ſet it forth by a double ſimilitude; the one by rending, the other by gathering; and that from verſ. 15. to the end. God will as it were rain Hell out of Heaven upon <hi>Babylon;</hi> he hath fire and brimſtone for this ſpirituall <hi>Sodome;</hi> judgement without mercy; and fury without compaſſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to the words of my Text, <hi>Theſe are they which follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth.</hi> This text is one of the Golden Characters of the hundred forty and four thouſand,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99213:36"/>which ſtood with the Lamb upon Mount <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words are three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Subjects, <hi>[theſe]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Act, <hi>[follow]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Object, <hi>[The Lamb] whitherſoever he goeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall gather this Obſervation from the words,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>That it is the ſweet temper and frame of ſoules truly gracious, to follow the</hi> Lamb <hi>whitherſoever he goeth.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In the handling of this point, I ſhall ſhew you five things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What it is to follow the Lamb:</p>
            <p>Secondly, Why they follow the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Excellency of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Miſery of them that follow not the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, How the Lambs followers may be known from the beaſts <hi>followers</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, To follow the Lamb whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth, is to follow him in four things.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99213:36"/>
            <p>Firſt, In his Commandements. <hi>If you love me, keep my Commandements,</hi> John 14.15. <hi>Ye are my friends if you do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I command you, Chap.</hi> 15.14. <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his Commandments, that they may have right to the Tree of Life,</hi> Rev. 22.4. Oh Beloved, we cannot follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goes, unleſs we follow him in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) when I have reſpect to all thy Commandments,</hi> Pſal. 119.6. Chriſtians ſhould take as much delight in thoſe precepts that enjoyne holineſſe, as in thoſe promiſes that aſſure happineſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In his teachings. <hi>My Sheep hear my Voyce, and I know them, and they follow me,</hi> John 10.27. <hi>A ſtranger they will not follow, but will flee from him, for they know not the voyce of ſtrangers,</hi> Verſ. 5.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In his Providences, through all afflictions, all ſtraits all diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſorrows whatſoever, though it be a way of blood. We muſt forſake all to follow a crucified Chriſt, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99213:37"/>in bloody paths of ſufferings, if he call us to it. <hi>Ye though I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me: Thy rod and thy ſtaffe they comfort me,</hi> Pſal. 23.4. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) I am ready not to be bound only, but alſo to dye at</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalam <hi>for the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> We muſt be willing to venture the loſs of all for him, Liberty, Eſtate, Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Life it ſelf: <hi>We have forſaken all, and followed thee,</hi> Math. 19.27.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In his Example. <hi>For I have given you an example, that you ſhould do as I have done to you,</hi> Joh. 13.5. that <hi>Becauſe Chriſt hath ſuffered for us, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.21, 22. So that to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſts ſteps, is to take him for an example: We muſt walk in the ſame ſpirit, in the ſame ſteps, and in the ſame obedience. VVe muſt not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wicked mens Examples, <hi>who walk in the broad way that leads to death, and are of their father the Devil, and his work they do,</hi> John 8.11. But we muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99213:37"/>our Head Chriſt, <hi>who went up and down doing good,</hi> Acts 10.38. Now this is to follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>In his Commands.</item>
               <item>In his Teachings.</item>
               <item>In his Providence.</item>
               <item>In his Example.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly, To follow the Lamb whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever he goeth, is to follow him truly, without hypocriſie; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, without apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Truly, without hypocriſie: Many follow the Lord as Beggars fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a man, onely for an Almes; they prize the wages of Religion, above the work of Religion. <hi>You ſeek me not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the miracles, but becauſe you did eat of the loaves and were filled,</hi> John 6.26. Oh Beloved, God abhors an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite more then a Sodomite; and Hell is provided on purpoſe for Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.51. My Beloved, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Lamb fully, is to have the heart ſixed and reſolved for God: <hi>My ſoul followes hard after thee,</hi> ſaid <hi>David,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:99213:38"/>Pſalm 63.8. <hi>And as the Hart panteth after the water brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after thee O God.</hi> All the faculties of his ſoule are working after God: <hi>My ſoul, and all that is within me praiſe the Lord,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſtantly, without Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy. A true Believer after he begins to follow the Lamb, he never leaves following him, but followeth him whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever he goeth. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? ſhall Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Diſtreſſe, or Perſecution, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or Nakedneſſe, or Perill, or Sword? For I am perſwaded that neither Death, nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor Things preſent, nor Things to come, nor Height, nor Depth, nor any Creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> Oh beloved, he doth not follow the Lamb whither ſoever he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that follows the Lord earneſtly for a while, but afterward forſaketh him when a ſtorme riſeth: <hi>Yet hath he not root in himſelf, but dureth for a while;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99213:38"/>when tribulation or perſecution ariſeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the word, by and by he is offended,</hi> Math. 13.21. Nor he that followes the Lamb in ſome things, and the Beaſt in other things: <hi>They feared the Lord, and ſerved their own gods, after the manner of the Nations.</hi> Nor he that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the Lord in a dull heavy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and a luke-warm temper: <hi>I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot, I would thou wert cold or hot,</hi> Chap. 3.15. <hi>Be aſtoniſhed, O ye Heavens, at this and be horribly afraid, be ye very deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, ſaith the Lord; for my people have committed two evils; they have forſaken me the fountaine of living waters, and hewed them out Giſterns, broken Ciſterns, that can hold no water,</hi> Jer. 2.12, 13. Oh this is not a following the Lamb: They that follow the Lord fully abide in the Lord, and cleave to the Lord, and continue conſtantly in Gods ways to the end of their dayes. <hi>The righteous holds on his way,</hi> Job 17.9. <hi>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord.</hi> Hoſea 6.3. The righteous man holds on his way, he followes the Lamb
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99213:39"/>whitherſoever he goeth:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, Speedily.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, Truly:</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, Undividedly:</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, Zealouſly.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly, Humbly.</item>
                  <item>Sixthly, Chearfully.</item>
                  <item>Seaventhly, Diligently.</item>
                  <item>Eightly, Conſtantly.</item>
                  <item>Ninthly, Faithfully.</item>
                  <item>Tenthly, Tranſcendently.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now this is following the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall ſhew you why Believers follow the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe they are redeemed by the blood of the Lamb. <hi>For as much as ye know that ye were not redeemed with corruptible things, as Silver, and Gold, from your vain converſation received by tradition from your fathers; but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a</hi> Lamb <hi>without blemiſh and without ſpot,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.18, 19. He paid a price for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, that ſo he might diſcharge
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99213:39"/>the debt of our ſins; <hi>And they ſung a new ſong, ſaying, Thou art worthy to take the Book, and to open the Seals thereof: for thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood, out of every Kindred, and Tongue, and People, and Nation,</hi> Rev. 5.9.</p>
            <p>There are three things called preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Scriptures.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, Faith is called precious, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</item>
               <item>Secondly, The promiſes are called precious, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, The blood of Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led precious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</item>
            </list>
            <p>O his blood hath redeemed us from ſix Enemies.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, From the World, <hi>Galathians</hi> 1.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4.</item>
               <item>Secondly, From the Curſe, <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> 3.13.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, From Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6: 18, 22.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, From the Devil, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.17, 18.</item>
               <item>Fifthly, From the ſting of Death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56.</item>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:99213:40"/>
               <item>Sixthly, From Hell, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.12. O his blood is precious blood; his blood hath ſlaine our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; he hath purchaſed by his blood Reconciliation with the Father, Union with the Son, and Communion with the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Ye that were ſometimes afar off, are made nigh by the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 2.13, 16.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly, They follow the Lamb, becauſe they are waſhed in the blood of the Lamb. <hi>He hath loved us, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed us from our ſins in his blood,</hi> Rev. 1.5. <hi>Theſe are they which came out of great Tribulation, and have waſhed their Robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 7.14. <hi>The blood of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſinne,</hi> 1 John 1.7. <hi>Chriſts</hi> blood waſheth away our bloody ſins. <hi>I ſaid unto thee, when thou waſt in thy blood, Live,</hi> Ezek. 16. For as ſoon as we are united with Chriſt, our ſins are upon him, and his righteouſneſs upon us. It is Chriſt that gives us life, and puts excellent Ornaments upon us to cover our nakedneſſe, and decketh us
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99213:40"/>with Jewels and Gems of Gold: So we become beautiful in his ſight, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.10. <hi>That he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinkle, nor any ſuch thing; but that it ſhould be holy, and without blemiſh,</hi> Eph. 5.27.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Believers follow the Lamb, becauſe they are riſen with the Lamb. <hi>If ye then be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on the right hand of God,</hi> Coloſſ. 3.1. <hi>Therefore we are buried with him by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme into death; that like as Chriſt was raiſed up from the dead by the glory of the father, even ſo we alſo ſhould wark in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life,</hi> Rom. 6.4. Every man beſides a Believer is a dead man, <hi>Dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins,</hi> Epheſ. 2.1. Therefore they are exhorted to riſe from the dead <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.4. They muſt riſe from evil to good, from Earthly-mindedneſſe to Heavenly-mindedneſs; but now Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers by faith are riſen from darkneſs to light: <hi>For ye were ſometimes dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but new are ye light in the Lord:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99213:41"/>Walk as Children of light,</hi> Eph. 5.8. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, ſhine, for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee,</hi> Iſa. 60.1. When the Lord ſhined forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his people in glorious diſcoveries of himſelf, he calls them away from their former condition. When the Lord diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered himſelf in a Goſpel diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his people were no longer to ſit under dark clouds of legal Ceremonies, but to follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They follow the Lamb, becauſe they are enlightned by the Lamb. <hi>God who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined in our hearts, to give us the light of the knowledge of the Glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. <hi>But we all with open face beholding as in a glaſs the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from Glory to Glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.18. <hi>Yea doubtleſſe, and I count all things but loſſe for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord; for whom I have ſuffered the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99213:41"/>loſſe of all things, and doe count them but dung that I may win Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.8. Divine and Heavenly knowledge brings a man near to God, it gives a man the cleareſt and the fulleſt ſight of God; and the nearer any man comes to God, the clearer viſion he hath of <hi>God,</hi> and the more communion with God.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why others doe not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lamb, is becauſe they ſee not the worth and want of the Lamb: <hi>Having the underſtanding darkned, being alienated from the living God, through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſs of their hearts,</hi> Epheſ. 4.18. Where there is a Vaile caſt before the eyes of knowledge, there is a Barre ſet before the hands of practiſe. An igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſon neither knows what he is a doing, nor doth he know whether he is a going; he doth nothing but undoe himſelf by doing. Carnal men ſee no preciouſneſs and lovelineſs in Chriſt; <hi>Oh what is thy beloved more then another beloved?</hi> Cant. 5,9. <hi>If thou knoweſt the gift of God, and who it is that asketh; thou
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99213:42"/>wouldeſt have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water,</hi> John 4.10.</p>
            <p>Chriſt goes undeſired in the world, becauſe he goes undiſcerned by the world: <hi>But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs unto him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. But now believers being enlightned by the Spirit of God, and by the Word of God, they ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what they were before faith, and what they are by faith, and what they ſhall be at the end of faith; they ſee Chriſt to be all precious, precious in his Ordinances, precious in his Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, precious in his Graces, precious in his Gifts, precious in his Promiſes, precious in his Members, precious in his Miniſters, and precious in himſelf, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. Therefore believers cannot but love him and follow him.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, They follow the Lamb be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they love the Lamb. <hi>Grace be with all them that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity,</hi> Epheſ. 6.24. They
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99213:42"/>love him with a ſuperlative love. <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee? and there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides thee,</hi> Pſal. 73.25. The Spouſe of Chriſt looks upon what ſhe is, as not great enough for his remembrance, and what ſhe does, as not good enough for his accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Look not upon me becauſe I am black, becauſe the Sun hath looked upon me; My Mothers Children were angry with me, they made me the keeper of their Vineyard, but mine one Vineyard have I not kept,</hi> Cant. 1.6. The Church is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more fair, than when ſhe judgeth her ſelf to be moſt deformed; never more happy, than when ſhe accounts her ſelf moſt miſerable; never more holy, than when ſhe reckons her ſelf moſt polluted; ſhe is never richer, than when ſhe ſeeth her ſelf to be pooreſt of all. The ſoul that loves much, is a ſoul that works much; the Commands of the Goſpel are not grievous to him, but precious to him. <hi>Tell me (oh thou whom my ſoul loveth) where thou feedeſt,</hi> Cant. 1.7. A ſoul that loves Chriſt hath
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99213:43"/>hath his eye upon Chriſt, and his deſire is after Chriſt. <hi>The deſire of our ſouls is to thy name, and to the remembrance of thee: With my Soul have I deſired thee in the Night, yea, with my Spirit will I ſeek thee early,</hi> Iſa. 26.8, 9. True believers love Chriſt more then they love themſelves, <hi>They loved not their lives unto the death,</hi> Rev. 13:11. Chriſt is dearer to them than their lives: they ſlighted, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, yea, deſpiſed their very lives, when they ſtood in competition with Chriſt, and his Glory, and choſe rather to ſuffer the greateſt miſery, than he ſhould loſe the leaſt dram of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. The love of Chriſt hath made his Saints and VVitneſſes yield all the parts and members of their bodies, to the cruel and mercileſſe inſtruments of bloody perſecutors; their backs to be whipt, their eyes to be boared, and their tongues to be cut out of their mouths, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37. Oh how ſtrongly did theſe love! the meaſure of loving Chriſt, is to love him without meaſure. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99213:43"/>Chriſt? Tribulation ſhall not, Perſecution ſhall not, Famine and Nakedneſſe ſhall not, Peril and Sword ſhall not: for I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other Creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord,</hi> Rom. 8.35, 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, They follow the Lamb, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are married to the Lamb: Jer. 3.14. <hi>I am married unto you,</hi> Rev. 21.9. <hi>I will ſhew thee the Bride, the Lambs Wife,</hi> Cant. 2.16. <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I will ſhew you two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, How Chriſts comes to be ours.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. How we come to be Chriſts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt is ours by the free do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and gift of the Father: <hi>God ſo loved the word, that he gave his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son,</hi> John 3.16.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt freely gave himſelf unto us; ſo that Chriſt is ours by his own conſent: he hath as it were paſſed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99213:44"/>over himſelf unto us; <hi>Chriſt loved me, and gave himſelf for me,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt hath paſſed himſelf over unto his Church by marriage; and therefore ſhe is called his Queen, his Spouſe, his Bride, and his VVife, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.9. Although we had nothing to bring to him but poverty, ſhame, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and miſery, yet he took us, and loved us, and married us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Chriſt is ours by commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating his own Spirit to us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Saints are <hi>Chriſts</hi> four ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By the Donation of the Father: <hi>God hath made him both Lord and Chriſt,</hi> Acts 2.36. <hi>And hath put all things under his feet, and gave him to be the Head over all things in the Church,</hi> Epheſ. 1.22. <hi>And now,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, Behold I and the Children whom thou gaveſt me; thine they were, and thou gaveſt them me,</hi> John Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen Six. God the Father gave us to God the Son, that he might redeem us; and God the Son gave us to God the Father, that he might ſanctifie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99213:44"/>us, and keep us from the evill of the World, <hi>verſe</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We are Chriſts by choice: <hi>I have choſen you out of the World:</hi> And the Saints are ſaid to be <hi>Choſen in Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 1.4. And they are called <hi>A choſen Generation,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.9. <hi>And choſen and faithful,</hi> Rev. 17.14.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Saints are Chriſts by purchaſe. We were in our Enemies hands, and under their power, and could not free our ſelves from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of the Law, Sin, Satan, Death, and Hell; therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We are bought with a price,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.20. For in reſpect of Gods Juſtice we are bought by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We are Chriſts by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination and Covenant. <hi>I entred into Covenant with thee, and thou becameſt mine,</hi> Ezek. 16.8. That is, I did make a Solemn Covenant or Stipulation with thee, that I would take thee to be my people. So that it is no wonder Pelievers follow the Lamb whetherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he goeth; they are married to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99213:45"/>him, he is their Head and Husband.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, They follow the Lamb, becauſe they have the Spirit of the Lamb: <hi>We have not the ſpirit of the World, but the Spirit which is of God, that we may know the things that are of God: And we have the mind of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.11, 12, 16. And we know that he abides in us, by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which he hath given us: <hi>Now if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> This Spirit that the Lord Jeſus gives to believers is a ſealing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a lively Spirit, and an enlightning Spirit, and a leading Spirit; it leads us from all evill to all good. And all the Lambs followers are in the Spirit of the Lamb; and therefore they pray in the Spirit, and with the Spirit, and by the Spirit, and for more of the Spirit: They that have this Spirit need not a Book to pray by. Now all true Believers have the Spirit of the Lamb, therefore they follow the Lamb whetherſoever he goeth,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Believers follow the Lamb,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99213:45"/>becauſe all their Priviledges come from the Lamb: They are all <hi>Kings and Prieſts:</hi> Rev. 1.6. Rev. 5.10. <hi>And Sons, and Heirs,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.1. <hi>Behold what manner of love the Father hath beſtowed upon us!</hi> Rom. 8.17. <hi>If Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then Heirs, Heirs with God, and joynt Heirs with Chriſt.</hi> Though Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have not a Crown in life, yet they are Heirs to a Crown of life: God puts the greateſt honour upon his own people, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.26. All the honour that other men have, is not worth the having: that which makes a man great in the eye of the world, makes a man nothing in the eye of God. Men are never the better for their greatneſs, if they are not made better by their greatneſs. But now believers great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and honour comes by Chriſt, the faithful and true witneſs, the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the dead, and the Prince of the Kings of the Earth: <hi>He hath made us unto our God Kings and Prieſts, and we ſhall reign on the Earth,</hi> Rev. 5.10.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99213:46"/>All the light, and life, and hope, and joy, and peace, and beauty, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and riches, Believers have, they have it all by Chriſt, and from Chriſt; he gives them rich Grace, and rich Glory, and all things richly to enjoy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17.</p>
            <p>Take a man that is out of Chriſt, and he hath none of all this, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>That at that time ye were without Chriſt, being aliens from the Common-wealth of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and ſtrangers from the Covenant of promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the World. They are wretched, and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked,</hi> Revel. 3.17.</p>
            <p>O this is the condition of every grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, Faithleſs, and Chriſtleſs perſon. But now a Believer though he be never ſo poor in the worlds eye, he is rich in Gods eye; for all things are his, and he ſhall inherit all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall inherit all things.</hi> But how comes it to paſs that the Believer hath ſo much, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99213:46"/>all others ſo little? He hath it all from Chriſt. <hi>Of his fulneſs have all we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Grace for Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore Believers doe glory in Chriſt, becauſe they have all their glory by and from Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.31. He hath enough to glory in, that hath a Chriſt to glory in: Now Believers cannot but cleave to him, and follow him, becauſe all their good things comes by him.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, They follow the Lamb, becauſe their names are written in the Lambs Book, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.8. <hi>And all that dwell upon the Earth ſhall worſhip him, whoſe names are not written in the Book of Life of the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the world. And there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth abomination, or maketh a lye: but they which are written in the Lambs book of life,</hi> Rev. 21.27. All the reſt, all the Worſhippers of the Beaſt, and all Unbelievers ſhall be caſt into
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99213:47"/>that Lake of fire which burns and flames for ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. There be a great many that follow the Beaſt, worſhip the Beaſt, receive the mark of the Beaſt, and admire the Beaſt, Chap. 13.3, 4. But what are they? Are they any that have their names written in the Lambs Book of Life? No, no; for this ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8. <hi>The Beaſt that thou ſaweſt, was, and is not, and ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſs pit, and ſhall go into perdition, and they that dwell on the Earth ſhall wonder, whoſe names were not written in the Book of Life.</hi> So that you ſee what that curſed crew are that follow <hi>Babylon,</hi> they are ſuch whoſe names are not written in the Book of Life. But they that have their Fathers name written in their fore-head, and their names written in the Lambs Book, they follow the Lamb whetherſoever he goeth: <hi>And they that are with him are called and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and faithful,</hi> Rev. 17.14.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, and laſtly, Precious ones
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99213:47"/>follow the Lamb, becauſe they ſhall be for ever with the Lamb. <hi>Then we which are alive and remain, ſhall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air, and ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lamb: Wherefore comfort one another with theſe words,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.17, 18. <hi>Therefore are they before the Throne of God, and ſerve him day and night in his Temple; and he that ſitteth on the Throne ſhall dwell among them: They ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sun light on them, nor any heat; for the Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feed them, and ſhall lead them unto living Fountains of waters, and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes,</hi> Re. 7.15, 16, 17. How troubleſom ſoever a Saints beginning is, his ending is joyful. When Believers change Earth for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they do not loſe their happineſs, but compleat their happineſs, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.17, 24. <hi>Eather, I will that they alſo whom thou gaveſt me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99213:48"/>which thou haſt given me; for thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedſt me before the foundation of the world:</hi> Not only with me for ever, but with my Saints, with my Angels, and with my Father, and with all that are with me.</p>
            <p>To be with God and Chriſt for ever, implyeth theſe ſeven things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The preſence of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The happy union with God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The bleſſed viſion of God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The glorious communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The fruition of God.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The reſt that the Saints ſhall have in God.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The enjoyments of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in God.</p>
            <p>Oh how unſpeakable is the glory of Heaven! Oh how infinitely glorious is the Lamb! Now true Believers follow the Lamb whetherſoever he goeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhall be for ever with the Lamb in fulneſs of glory, and endleſs felicity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99213:48"/>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewed you why Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers follow the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall ſhew you the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of following the Lamb.</p>
            <p>The firſt Excellency is, They that follow the Lamb have the preſence of the Lamb with them.</p>
            <p>The hundred forty and four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand that ſtood upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> had the Lamb with them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.5. <hi>God is in the midſt of her, ſhe ſhall not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; God ſhall help her, and that right early. The Lord of Hoſts is with us; the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>is our refuge,</hi> Verſe 7. God is in the midſt of his Church, not only to behold her, but to uphold her. Though the Churches Enemies may be waves to toſs her, yet they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be Rocks to ſplit her, becauſe God is in the midſt of her. This is that which comforted and ſtrengthened <hi>David; Yea, though I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death, I will fear no evill, for thou art with me,</hi> Pſalm 23.4. <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the Waters I will be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99213:49"/>with thee; and through the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, they ſhall not overflow thee; when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee,</hi> Iſa. 43.2. Oh they that follow the Lamb, ſhall ſtand for the Lamb, have the preſence of the Lamb; his glorious preſence, his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious preſence, his comforting preſence, his protecting preſence, his quickning and ſanctifying preſence.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Excellency is, That they that follow the Lamb, ſhall know the mind of the Lamb.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is given unto you to know the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven, but to them it is not given: And bleſſed are your eyes, for they ſee, and your ears for they hear,</hi> Mat. 13.11, 16. <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I call you not ſervants, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant knoweth not what his Lord doth; but I have called you friends; for all things that I have heard of my Father, I have made known unto you,</hi> John 17.6, 7, 8. Jeſus Chriſt that lies in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of his Father, he unboſomes and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99213:49"/>unbowels the heart of the Father to Believers; they know his Secrets, his Mind, his Counſel, and his WIll; and none knoweth it but them: <hi>I thank thee O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them unto Babes,</hi> Matth. 11.25. But they that walk with God, know much of the mind of God, and the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Third Excellency of following the Lamb, is, They that follow the Lamb, may come boldly to the Lamb. <hi>Let us therefore come boldly unto the Throne of Grace, that we may obtain mercy, and find Grace to help in time of need,</hi> Heb. 4.16. A ſoul that hath an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, may come boldly to Chriſt, and ſpeak boldly to him, and to his Father, for any mercy he need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; he may go to the Throne of Grace for Grace, and open his heart to God, as one friend to another. Oh what a liberty have Believers! Oh what a priviledge have they, that they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:99213:50"/>May go to God with a holy boldneſs! The wicked proud ones of the Earth are ſo high that the poor Saints cannot come boldly and freely to them; but they may come boldly and freely to the Lord their God: <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Excellency is, They that follow the Lamb ſhall have all their wants ſupplyed by the Lamb. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.19. <hi>But my God ſhall ſupply all your need, according to his riches in glory, by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> They that follow the Lamb ſhall want no good thing: <hi>Oh fear the Lord all ye his Saints, for there is no want to them that fear him. The young Lyons do lack and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any good thing,</hi> Pſal. 34.9.10. <hi>The Lord is my ſhepherd, I ſhall not want,</hi> Pſal. 23.1. Delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and he ſhall give thee the deſire of thy heart; thou ſhalt have whatſoever thou deſireſt to have. He that hath the chiefeſt good, ſhall want no good.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:99213:50"/>
               <hi>Whoſoever ſhall drink of the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt: And he that cometh to me ſhall never hunger,</hi> Joh. 6.35. Oh who would not follow and believe in the Lamb; Oh happy are all they that follow the Lamb.</p>
            <p>The fifth Excellency is, They that follow the Lamb ſhall ſhare with the Lamb,</p>
            <p>Firſt, In his Divine Nature. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by are given unto us exceeding great and precious promiſes, that by theſe you might be partakers of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, having eſcaped the corruption that is in the world through luſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4. That is, of thoſe Divine Qualities, whereby we are made like unto God in Wiſdom, and Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In his Conqueſts, The poor Saints ſhare with Chriſt in all his noble and honourable conqueſts (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5.55.) over the World, Death, and Hell, and over ſufferings: <hi>In all theſe things we are more then Conquerours through him that loved us,</hi> Rom. 8.37.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:99213:51"/>
            <p>Thirdly, They ſhare with Chriſt in his Graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of his fulneſs have all we received grace for grace,</hi> Joh. 1.16. As a Child receives Member for Member; as the Paper from the Preſs receives Letter for Letter; as the Wax from the Seal receives Print for Print; or as the Glaſs from the Image receives Face for Face; ſo do Believers receive from Chriſt Grace for Grace; that is, for every grace that is in the Lamb, there is the ſame grace in us in ſome meaſure.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Believers ſhare with Chriſt in his Glorious Titles.</p>
            <p>He is called a Son, ſo are they; a King, ſo are they; a Prieſt, ſo are they; an Heir, ſo are they, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, They ſhare with Chriſt in his Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I go to prepare a place for you: I will come again and receive you unto my ſelf, that where I am, there ye may be alſo,</hi> Joh. 14.23. <hi>And the glory which thou gaveſt me, I have given them, that they
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99213:51"/>may be one, as we are one,</hi> Joh. 17.22. <hi>My ſheep hear my voice, and they follow me, and I give unto them eternal life,</hi> Joh. 10.28. The Saints ſhall have the ſame Glory which Chriſt himſelf hath: The Saints in Heaven are not only glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with Chriſt (which is a great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation) but they do enjoy the very ſame Glory which Chriſt himſelf doth; the ſame for kind, though not for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. The Head and Members are glorified together with the ſame kind of glory: God hath not one Heaven for his Son, and another for his Saints; but one and the ſame heaven for both. Believers ſhall be as truly glorious as Chriſt is, and eternally glorious as he is. <hi>Our vile bodies ſhall be faſhioned like unto his glorious body: And we ſhall be glorified together with him, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with him in Glory,</hi> Rom. 8. Col. 3. Oh here is the excellency of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lamb; they that follow him ſhare with him.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Excellency of following the Lamb, is, They that follow the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99213:52"/>Lamb ſhall be protected by the Lamb. <hi>He ſuffered no man to do them wrong, yea, he reproved Kings for their ſakes, ſaying, touch not mine Anointed, and do my Prophets no harm,</hi> Pſal. 105.14, 15. which are his Saints. <hi>Who is he that will harm you, if ye be followers of that which is good? and if ye ſuffer for righteouſneſs ſake, happy are ye, and be not afraid of their terrour, neither be troubled,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.13. <hi>Fear thou not, for I am with thee: be not diſmayed, for I am thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee, yea, I will help thee, yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 41.10. <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb? yea they may forget, yet will I not forget thee,</hi> Iſa, 49.15. Who can harm a man if God be with him and for him: He that hath the love of God, need not care for the anger of men: A true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever hath the love of God, the love of Chriſt, the love of good Angels, the love of good men, and the love of all
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:99213:52"/>whoſe love is worth the having: God protects men in his way, but not out of his way: When men appear for God God appears for men; he is good to them in affliction, and he doth them good by affliction.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Excellency is, They that follow the Lamb ſhall not feel the wrath of the Lamb. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.11. <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall not be hurt of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.10. <hi>And to wait for his Son from Heaven: whom he rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the dead, even Jeſus which delivered us from the wrath to come. There is therefore now no condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit,</hi> Rom. 8.1. Oh how ſad is the condition of thoſe, who live and dye without Chriſt! they are ſent to Hell, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all the Nations that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God: Who ſhall be puniſhed with everlasting deſtruction from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.9. They ſhall feel
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99213:53"/>and ſuffer the wrath of the Lamb, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they deſpiſed the truth of the Lamb. <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed; I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded; but ye have ſet at nought all my counſel, and would none of my reproof: I alſo will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh; when your fear cometh as deſolation, and your deſtruction cometh as a whirl-wind; when diſtreſs and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh cometh upon you: then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not anſwer; they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me,</hi> Pro. 1.24, 25, 26, 27, 28. Do you hear this ſinners? if God will ſhew you no mercy if you live in your ſins, and dye in your ſins, be ſure Hell will ſhew you no mercy: Now the Believer ſhall feel and ſuffer none of this, he is in a happy ſtate and condition.</p>
            <p>The eighth Excellency is, They that follow the Lamb ſhall reign with the Lamb: and this is another Excellency of following the Lamb. True Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers do reign now over the Creatures,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:99213:53"/>over the pomp and pride of the world, over all ſpirits, over ſin, over the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of wicked men, and over ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings: but beſides all this, they ſhall reign with Chriſt, and over thoſe that now reign over them: <hi>Rev</hi> 5.10. <hi>And we ſhall reign on the Earth,</hi> Chap. 20.4. <hi>And they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</hi> And as the wicked tread down the Saints under their feet, ſo ſhall the ſaints tread down the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under their feet, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.3 The Lord hath promiſed that the meek ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Earth. Doth not the Scripture ſay, that <hi>In the laſt dayes the mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be lifted up above the hills, and ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountains?</hi> Iſa. 2.2. <hi>And that the Kingdoms of this world, muſt become the Kingdomes of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> Rev. 11.15. And he that loves to ſee the face of his Church beautiful, will ere long wipe away thoſe bloody tears; it is not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you will triumph and ſay, (<hi>Cant.</hi> 2.11.12.) <hi>Lo, the winter is paſt, the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:99213:54"/>rain is over and gone, the flowers appear on the Earth, the time of the ſinging of Birds is come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ninth Excellency is, They that follow the Lamb, ſhall ſit upon the Throne with the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20 21. <hi>To him that overcometh will I grant to fit with me in my Throne, even as I alſo overcame, and am ſet down with my Father in his throne. Ye alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael,</hi> Mat. 19.28. Oh what an honour is this! what a glory is this to ſit upon the Throne with Chriſt! Is it not honour and glory enough for us to be in heaven with God, and Chriſt, and Angels? but muſt we ſit upon a Throne there? Oh what an honour is this! and yet this honour ſhall all the Lambs followers have.</p>
            <p>The tenth Excellency of following the Lamb, is, They that follow the Lamb ſhall judge the world with the Lamb. If you conſult ſacred Record you ſhall find that both God &amp; Chriſt
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:99213:54"/>and the Saints are ſaid to judge the world: The Ordination is Gods, the Execution is Chriſts, the Approbation is the Saints. When the Apoſtle would ſtop the ſinful ſuits among the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> brethren, that did not want men of Eminency to put a period unto Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, ſaith, <hi>Do ye not know that the Saints ſhall judge the world? and if the world ſhall be judged by you, are ye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to judge the ſmalleſt matters?</hi> 1 Cor. 6.2. Enoch <hi>the ſeventh from</hi> Adam <hi>Propheſied, ſaying, Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thouſand of his Saints to execute Judgement upon all,</hi> Jude 14.15. <hi>When the Son of man ſhall ſit in the Throne of his glory, ye alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Iſrael,</hi> Matth. 19.28. Now the world judge the Saints, but then the Saints ſhall judge the world; now they judge and condemn Chriſt in his Members, but then they ſhall be judged and condemned by Chriſt and his Members; For as the World cannot endure God himſelf,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:99213:55"/>ſo neither can they endure God in the Saints: and the more God dwells in the Saints, the more the world afflicts the Saints: but they that follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth, ſhall ſit upon thoſe, that now ſit upon them.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewed you the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of following the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The miſery of thoſe that follow not the Lamb, but the Beaſt: O their miſery is great in this life; but it will be greater in the other.</p>
            <p>The firſt miſery of them that follow the Beaſt, is, They that follow him, ſhall ſhare with him in all his plagues. <hi>And the third Angel followed them, ſaying with a loud voice, if any man worſhip the Beaſt, and his Image, and receive his mark in his fore-head, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out without mixture into the Cup of his indignation, and he ſhall be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with fire and brimſtone in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lemb,</hi> Rev. 14.9, 10. Oh the plagues, the terrible plagues, that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:99213:55"/>ſhall fall upon the Beaſt! <hi>Death, and mourning, and famine, and fire,</hi> Chap. 18.8. The judgements ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all parties, and upon all degrees and conditions of men, that joyn with the Beaſt: All thoſe that do partake of his ſins, ſhall ſhare of his plagues.</p>
            <p>There is Firſt, a Vial poured out upon the Earth; that is, upon the common people, Chap. 16. verſ. 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another Viall upon the Sea; that is, the Juriſdiction of <hi>Rome,</hi> Verſe 3.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Another Vial upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; that is, their Miniſters, Verſ. 4.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Another Vial is poured out upon the Sun, that is, Princes and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Verſ. 8.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Another Vial alſo upon the Seat; that is, <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, the throne of the Beaſt, Verſ. 10.</p>
            <p>So that all that worſhip the Beaſt, and receive his Mark, and belong to him, whether they be high or low, rich or poor, if they do not come off from him, they ſhall ſhare with him in all
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:99213:56"/>his plagues: <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, that ye receive not of her plagues,</hi> Rev. 18.4.</p>
            <p>The ſecond miſery of them that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Beaſt, is, they ſhall cry to the Rocks and to the Mountains of the Earth. <hi>And the great men, and rich men, and the chief Captains, and the mighty men, and every Bondman, and every Freeman hid themſelves in the Dens and in the Rocks of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and ſaid to the Mountains and Rocks, fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb; for the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi> Rev. 6.15, 16, 17. They that are here cloathed in Silk and Velvet, ſhall wiſh for the mountains to cover them; which would be but a poor ſhelter, <hi>for the Mountains melt at the preſence of the Lord, and the Rocks rend aſunder when he is angry.</hi> They that made others fly away from them as innocent Lambs from devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wolves, ſhall be afraid of the wrath
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:99213:56"/>of the Lamb that ſitteth on the throne. Oh how will thoſe great men dare to appear before his Tribunal, that have ſtained the Sword of Authority with the blood of innocency, by turning its back againſt the vicious, and whetting its edge againſt the righteous? Many an unjuſt Judge that now ſits confidently upon the Bench, ſhall then ſtand trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at the Bar. Oh how will they be able to lift up their heads before Chriſt, who have lifted up their hands againſt Chriſt? <hi>The Kings of the earth ſtood up, and the Rulers were gathered together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt,</hi> Act. 4.26. Rev. 17.14. Inſtead of help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord againſt the Mighty, they help the Mighty againſt the Lord, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 2.2. Oh how many great men are there, that make no other uſe of their greatneſſe, but to be great in wickedneſſe? great Swearers, great Drunkards, great Sabbath-breakers, great Perſecutors, great Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, great Atheiſts; who inſtead of denying or forſaking the Devil and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99213:57"/>all his works, follow the Devil and all his works; who ſin with content, and are content with their ſins. <hi>Thy Princes are rebellious, and companions of Thieves,</hi> Iſa. 1.23. But the great God againſt whom they ſin, is greater than the greateſt; <hi>before whom all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world are but as a drop of a Bucket, and as the ſmall duſt of the Ballance.</hi> Iſa. 40.15. <hi>Who will not fear thee, O King of Nations? foraſmuch as there is none like unto thee O Lord: Thou art great, and thy name is great, and thy power is great,</hi> Jer. 10.6. He toucheth the mountains, and they ſmoak; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom the Devils fear &amp; tremble. Therefore wo, wo, be to them that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, and follow the Beaſt; they ſhall cry and call for help, but there will be none to help them.</p>
            <p>The third miſery of thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Beaſt, is. They ſhall be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Lake of fire with the Beaſt. <hi>And the Beaſt was taken, and with him the falſe Prophet, that wrought miracles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, with which he deceived them
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:99213:57"/>that had received the mark of the Beaſt and them that worſhipped his Image; theſe both were caſt alive into a lake of fire burning with brimſtone,</hi> Rev. 19.20 <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from heaven, with his mighty Angels, in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.7, 8, 9. Oh what a dreadful thing is it to lye under the wrath of God! to lye in burning flames! and for ever to be baniſhed from the preſence of God, and his holy Angels! This will be the portion of the Beaſts followers. Oh will they not wiſh then that they had never been born? and that they might be turned into ſtocks and ſtones? but alas all their wiſhes will do them no good; Chriſt will ſay to them then, <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> Mat. 25.41, 42, 43. O ye Rulers and great
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99213:58"/>Ones of the Earth, It will be no diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your Honours, to lay your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at his feet, in whoſe preſence the Angels vail their faces, and before whoſe Throne the Elders caſt their Crowns, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10. O is it not better then with patience to ſuffer with <hi>Sion,</hi> and the Churches party, a while, rather than joyn with the <hi>Romiſh</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and be ruined with them in the end? <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints.</hi> Ye ſhall ſuffer a while, and be troden down by them; and you muſt ſtay for the full accompliſhment of this promiſe for your deliverance, <hi>But I will ſurely come, and will recompence all your patience:</hi> And therefore be not diſcouraged and faint in your minds, let not your hearts turn back un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt,</hi> and hanker after <hi>Rome,</hi> thoſe remnants of <hi>Baal,</hi> which God will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I ſhall ſhew you now how the Lambes Followers may be known from the Beaſts follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:99213:58"/>
            <p>Firſt, You may know them by their number: They are in number the few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. <hi>Many are called, but few are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> Mat. 20.16. <hi>Though all Iſrael be as the ſand of the Sea, yet but a remnant ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Rom. 9.27. And Chriſt calls his flock, <hi>a little flock,</hi> Luke 12.32. And truly Beloved, they are but a few that follow the Lamb, and believe in him. The Heathens follow the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: the <hi>Turks</hi> follow <hi>Mahomet;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> follow <hi>Moſes;</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> follow the <hi>Pope;</hi> and looſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and carnal <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> they follow the <hi>world</hi> the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil;</hi> and <hi>falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, falſe Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>falſe Worſhips; And all the world wondred after the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.3. <hi>The waters which thou ſaweſt, where the Whore ſitteth, are Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and Multitudes, and Nations, and Tongues,</hi> Chap. 17.15. Believers though their natures are the ſweeteſt, yet their number is the ſmalleſt: In Heaven are the beſt, but in Hell are the moſt.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:99213:59"/>
            <p>O dear Chriſtians, there are but few upright Chriſtians; there are many Thorns, but few Lillies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By their Characters you may know them. You have nine love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Characters of them in this four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they ſtand with the Lamb up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mount <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, They have their Fathers name written in their foreheads.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They ſing a new Song, which none can learn, but onely the hundred forty and four thouſand.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They are ſuch as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Earth.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, They are Virgin-Saints, not defiled with women.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, They follow the Lamb whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever he goeth.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, They are redeemed from amongſt men.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, They bring their firſt fruits unto God, and to the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, <hi>And in their mouthes was found no guile; for they are without
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:99213:59"/>fault before the Throne of God.</hi> O how holy, how heavenly, how gracious, how glorious, how lovely and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al are theſe! they live in the Lord; on the Lord, to the Lord, and with the Lord; <hi>They are a choſen Generation, a Royal Prieſthood, an holy Nation, a peculiar people,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By their Spirit: They have another ſpirit, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.24. All the Lambs followers are in the ſpirit of the Lamb, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9, 16. And by that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they are led and taught; a ſpirit of holineſs, a ſpirit of meekneſs, a ſpirit of love, a free ſpirit, and a true humble and faithful ſpirit to, and for the Lord. Now as the Lambs followers are in the ſpirit of the Lamb; ſo the Beaſts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers are in the ſpirit of the Beaſt, which is no other then the ſpirit of the Devil, <hi>(Eph.</hi> 2.2. <hi>According to the Prince of the power of the Air, the ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:)</hi> a ſpirit of Lording and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering, a ſpirit of cunning and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, a ſpirit of Deceit, a ſpirit of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:99213:60"/>a ſpirit of perſecution and cruelty; and in this ſpirit are all the followers of the Beaſt. Now by this you may know the Lambs followers from the Beaſts followers.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By their name: They have another name, <hi>A new name,</hi> Rev. 3.12. God gives his people honourable Titles, though the Beaſt giveth them reproachful Titles. God calls them <hi>The dearly beloved of his ſoul,</hi> Jer. 12.7. And <hi>The Apple of his eye,</hi> Zech. 2.8. And <hi>His Jewels,</hi> Mal. 3.17. His Glory, his Portion, his Bride, his Friends and Children: But the Beaſt calls them Seditious Hereticks, Deceivers and Deluders, Blaſphemers, and Fools, and Mad-men, as if they were not worthy to have a being amongſt men: But though they are Ravens in the Worlds eye, yet they are Doves in Gods eye; yea, they are ſuch Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies <hi>Of whom this world is not worthy,</hi> Heb. 11.38. Now dear Chriſtians, by this you may know the Lambs follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from others, by the Nick-names the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:99213:60"/>world giveth them, and by the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous names that God giveth them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, by their Graces they may be known. Such as are the Lambs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers are full of faith, full of love, full of grace and goodneſſe, they are very fruitful, and bring forth much fruit, <hi>John</hi> 15. They are called Heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their heavenlineſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. And holy becauſe of their holineſſe; ſpiritual, becauſe of their ſpiritualneſs; and faithful, becauſe of their faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: There is much of God to be ſeen in them, in their words, works, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and converſations, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>For our converſation is in Heaven.</hi> They ſeek Heavenly things, and walk by a Heavenly Rule, they eye Heavenly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and are lead by a Heavenly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; they ſubmit to a Heavenly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and imitate Heavenly ones; there is much of Heaven in them, and much of them in heaven: <hi>When I awake, I am ſtill with thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now the Beaſts followers they, are full too, but it is with blould and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:99213:61"/>ſwearing, curſing, ſtealing, lying, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming, rebellion, and all manner of abominations and filthineſſe, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. Now Beloved, by this you may know Chriſts precious ones, from the Beaſts filthy ones.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The Lambs followers may be known from the Beaſts followers, by their keeping the Commandments of God, and the Faith of Jeſus <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints; here are they that keep the Commandments of God, and the Faith of Jeſus.</hi> So Rev. 12.17. <hi>The Dragon was wroth with the Woman, and made war with the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of her ſeed, which keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, &amp; having the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> True Believers cleave to the Lord, and follow him ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>But my ſervant Caleb hath followed me fully,</hi> Numb. 14.24. <hi>And Enoch walked with God,</hi> Gen. 5.24. <hi>And No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah walked with God,</hi> Gen. 6.9. <hi>Let us alſo walk in the Spirit,</hi> Gal 5.25. And they follow the Lamb whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he goeth, they hear his voice,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:99213:61"/>they profeſſe his worſhip, and obey his doctrine, they obhor Antichriſt, they follow not the Beaſt, nor receive his mark, but keep their beautiful gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Goſpel innocency, and will not touch beaſtly <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, By their Company: The Lambs followers keep company toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Being let go, they went to their own company,</hi> Acts 4.23. So they are ſaid to ſtand upon a Sea of Glaſſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>And I ſaw as it were a Sea of glaſs, mingled with fire, and them that had gotten victory over the Beaſt, and over his image, and over his mark, and over the number of his name, ſtand on the Sea of Glaſſe, having the harps of God,</hi> Rev. 15.2. So they that are with the Lamb upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> are together, and keep together, and follow the Lamb together. Chriſts faithfull Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes do not hear with Antichriſts hearers, nor worſhip with them which worſhip the Beaſt; for they are come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Chap. 18.4. <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:99213:62"/>of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues: Whereof come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and be ye ſeparate, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you, ſaith the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.17. The Children of God wil not keep company with the Children of wrath, for they cannot agree; <hi>For what fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath righteouſneſs with unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs? and what communion hath light with darkneſſe? and what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? or what part hath he that believeth, with an Infidel? and what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols?</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14, 15, 16. there fore believers keep together, walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; worſhip God together: <hi>And they that believed were of one heart, and one ſoul, &amp; continued in the Apoſtles Doctr. and fellowſhip,</hi> Acts 4.32. Acts 2.42. By this the Lambs followers are known to wit, by their company.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, By their Language they are known: True Believers ſpeak the Language of <hi>Canaan;</hi> their Language is Scripture-Language; you may know
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:99213:62"/>them by their ſpeech, as <hi>Peter</hi> was known by his ſpeech: <hi>Surely thou art one of them for thy ſpeech bewrayeth thee,</hi> Mat. 26.73. Their words are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heavenly; they ſpeak of God, and to God, and for God, and <hi>He heareth them,</hi> Mal. 3.16. But the beaſts followers ſpeak wickedly, proudly, daringly, and blaſphemouſly Chap. 13.4. <hi>And he opened his mouth blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, his Son, his Name, his Saints, and they that dwell in Heaven,</hi> verſe 6. Men are known who and what they are, and to whom they do belong, by their Language; if they are of God, and in God, they cannot but ſpeak much of God.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, The Lambs followers are known by this, They are more afflicted with the Churches heavineſs, than they are affected with their own happineſs. <hi>The King ſaid why is thy countenance ſad? this is nothing elſe but ſorrow of heart, ſeeing thou art not ſick. Why ſhould not my countenance be ſad, when the City, the place of my fathers, lyeth
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:99213:63"/>waſte, and the Gates thereof are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fire?</hi> Nehem. 2.2, 3. How can <hi>Sions</hi> Sons be rejoycing, when their Mother is mourning? Though they were the <hi>Jews</hi> Deſolation, yet they were <hi>Jeremies</hi> Lamentation. How can ſuch rejoyce in her ſtanding, that do not mourn for her falling: When the Churches Adverſaries make long fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows upon her back, we ſhould caſt in the ſeed of tears. <hi>Remember them that are in bonds, as being bound with them; and them which ſuffer adverſitie, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves alſo in the body,</hi> Heb. 13.3. Sympathiſing with others makes an eſtate that is joyful more happy, and an eſtate that is doleful leſs heavy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The righteous periſh, and no man layeth it to heart,</hi> Iſa. 5.7. We may draw up that charge againſt many now. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.46. <hi>They lye upon beds of Ivory, and ſtretch themſelves upon Couches, and eat the Lambs out of the flock, and the Calves out of the midſt of the ſtall; that drink wine in bowls, and anoint them
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:99213:63"/>ſelves with the chief Ointments; but they are not grieved for the afflictions of</hi> Joſeph. O that there were not too many ſuch now adays, that eat the fat, and drink the ſweet, and are not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for <hi>Sions</hi> troubles: Inſtead of ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathiſing with them in their miſery, they are cenſuring of them for their miſery. But the true Servants of God are tender and broken-hearted, they weep and mourn, and wring their hands for <hi>Sions</hi> ſins, for <hi>Sions</hi> Breaches for <hi>Sions</hi> Calamities, for <hi>Sions</hi> Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and thus they do and will do, till they ſee <hi>Sion</hi> on Mount <hi>Sion</hi> with the Lamb to be.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, the Lambs followers are known by their love to Chriſt, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings for Chriſt; they chuſe the worſt of ſorrows, before they will commit the leaſt of ſins: <hi>For thy ſake are we killed all the day long, and counted as ſheep for the ſlaughter,</hi> Pſa, 44. Rom. 8.36. <hi>And ye ſhall be hated of all men for my Names ſake,</hi> Mat. 10 22. <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:99213:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:99213:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:99213:65"/>you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you falſly for my ſake,</hi> Mat. 5.10. Love can walk on the water without drowning, and lye in the fire without burning. How ſhall we land at the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of reſt, if we are not toſſed upon the Sea of trouble, A believer ſhould live above the love of life and the fear of death. Though we cannot live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out afflictions, yet let us live above afflictions: None are ſo welcome to that ſpiritual <hi>Canaan,</hi> as thoſe that ſwim to it through the Red Sea of their own bloud. In ſuffering the offence is done to us, in ſinning the offence is done to God: In ſuffering we loſe the favour of men, in ſinning we loſe the favour of God: Therefore <hi>Daniel</hi> choſe the Den of the Lion, rather than he would forſake the Cauſe of the Lamb, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. And the three Chrildren choſe rather to ſuffer ſadly, than to ſin foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. And <hi>Moſes</hi> choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:99213:65"/>to be a Martyr than a Monarch; it is better to be a priſoner for Chriſt, than to be a Prince without Chriſt, or againſt Chriſt. O how precious, how glorious, how lovely, and how ſweet is Jeſus Chriſt to believers? O they love him entirely uprightly, they love his glorious perſon, and the beauty of his holineſſe, and his Name, his Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, his Cauſe, and his Members; they will ſuffer for him, and die for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſuffered and died for them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11. <hi>And they loved not their lives unto the Death.</hi> Now by this all men may know the Lambs follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from the Beaſts followers, <hi>viz.</hi> by their ſorrowes and ſufferings for Chriſt, for Truth, for Righteouſneſs, and for Conſcience ſake, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. <hi>And they took joyfully the ſpoyling of their goods, Heb.</hi> 11.35.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, The Lambs followers are known by this, They ſeek the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good of others above the private good of themſelves. <hi>I have great heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and continual ſorrow in my heart;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:99213:66"/>for I could wiſh that my ſelf were accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from Chriſt, for my brethren, my Kinſmen according to the fleſh,</hi> Rom. 9.2.3. <hi>And now O Father, glorifie thy ſon that thy ſon may glorifie thee,</hi> Joh. 17.1. He prayed for glory more for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake that beſtowed it, than for his own ſake that received it. A true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doth not deſire grace only for this end, that God may glorifie him; but he deſires grace for this end, that he may glorifie God. <hi>For ye know the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that though he was rich, yet for your ſakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might be rich,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.9. O, that the Lord Jeſus ſhould not only in pitty ſave us, but in love dye for us! <hi>And</hi> David, <hi>after he had ſerved his own Generation by the Will of God, fell on ſleep Acts</hi> 13.36. His Generation did not ſerve him, but he ſerved his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; not the Generation that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, for they were dead before he was living; nor the Generation that was behind him, for they were living after
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:99213:66"/>he was dead: but his own Generation; and not by his own will, but by the Will of God. Old <hi>Ely</hi> mourned more for the loſe of his Religion, than for the loſe of his Relation, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18, So <hi>Moſes Exo.</hi> 32.10. <hi>Now therefore let me alone, that my wrath may wax hot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and that I may conſume them; and I wil make of thee a great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> He was no ſelf-ſeeker, but a life preſerver. Grace doth not only make a man carry it like a man to God, but to carry it like a God to man. Reaſon makes a man a man, but grace makes a man a Chriſtian. Every gracious ſpirit is publick, though every publick ſpirit is not gracious. As we are not born by our ſelves, ſo we are not born for our ſelves. But the Beaſts followers and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons</hi> Merchants are for themſelves, and ſeek themſelves: <hi>Yea they are gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Dogs, which can never have enough, and they are ſhepherds that cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſtand; they all look to their own way every one for his gain from his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Iſa.</hi> 56.11. And <hi>teaching things
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:99213:67"/>they ought not, for filthy lucres ſake, Tit.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Wo to you</hi> Scribes <hi>and</hi> Phariſees, <hi>for ye devoure widdows houſes, and for a pretence make long prayers: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ſhall receive the great damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Mat.</hi> 23. Theſe make not gain to ſtoop to Godlineſſe, but Godlineſſe to ſtoop to gain.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, and Laſtly, The Lambs followers may be known from the Beaſts followers by this, They are more for power, than form; for heart, than Art; for matter, than method; for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, than ſhew, <hi>Having a form of Godlineſſe, but denying the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; from ſuch turn away,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim,</hi> 3.5. As they who have the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, cannot deny the form; ſo they who have the form of Godlineſs, ſhould not deny the power. Alas, what is hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without doing? and praying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out practiſing? and preaching without reforming? God loves to ſee the plants of righteouſneſſe, lodened with the fruits of righteouſneſſe: He bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth greater reſpect to our hearts,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:99213:67"/>than he doth to our works. <hi>I beſeech you therefore, Brethren, by the mercies of God, that ye preſent your bodies a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſacrifice, holy, and acceptable unto God,</hi> Rom. 12.1. The Formaliſt he is all for outward action, and for nothing of inward ſincerity; he is for a body without a ſoul, and a ſhew without a ſubſtance: but it is not a ſhew of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward piety, that will excuſe inward hypocriſie. <hi>For he is not a Jew that is one outwardly, neither is that Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion which is outward in the fleſh: But he is a Jew which is one inwardly, and Circumciſion is that of the heart, in the ſpirit, and not in the letter whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God,</hi> Rom. 2.28, 29. <hi>I know the blaſphemy of them which ſay they are Jews, and are not, but are the Synagogue of Satan Rev.</hi> 2.9. They are better in their outſides, than they are in their inſides; but Believers are better in their inſides, than they are in their outſides: <hi>The Kings daughter is all glorious within, her cloathing is of wrought Gold,</hi> Pſalm. 45.13. The
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:99213:68"/>one bowes his knee at the name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the other bowes his heart to the truth of Jeſus; the one ſignes with the Croſs, the other carryes the Croſs. Oh what would not ſuperſtitious men do for Heaven, if they might have Heaven for their doing? But they that ſail in this rotten Bottom, will ſurely ſink in the Ocean. <hi>Who hath required this at your hands, to tread my Courts? To what purpoſe is your ſacrifices unto me, ſaith the Lord? I am ful of the burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Rams, and the fat of fed beaſts and I delight not in the blood of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks, or of Lambs, or of He-goates,</hi> Iſa. 1, 11. It was not the Clay &amp; Spittle that cured the blind man, but Chriſts anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his eyes. It was not the troubling of the Waters in the Pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> that made them whole, but the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of the Angel. Alas, the diſh without the meat will not feed us. Man may ſpread the Net of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but its God muſt take the Draught of Mercy. Now by this Beloved you may know the Lambs follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:99213:68"/>from the Beaſts followers.</p>
            <p>And thus I have briefly and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed you theſe five things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, What following the Lamb is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Why gracious Souls follow the Lamb whitherſoever he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Excellency of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Fourthly The Miſery of following the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, How the Lambs follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers may be known from the Beaſts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
            <p>I ſhall make ſome Uſe of this:</p>
            <p>Firſt, For Examination, and Selfe-tryal. Oh friends; for the Lords ſake, and for your ſouls ſake, examine your ſelves, and try your ſelves by this, that you may know whoſe you are, and to whom you do belong. <hi>Know you not, that to whom ye yield your ſelves ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to obey, his ſervants ye are to whom ye obey; whether of ſin unto death, or of obedience unto righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 6.</p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:99213:69"/>
            <p>O who do you follow? if men, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily you have your reward; if ſin, you ſhall have ſins wages, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal death; woe, and miſery in this life, and Hell and deſtruction in the other life: but if God, then you ſhall have eternal life. <hi>Therefore be not deceived,</hi> miſtake not your ſelves, <hi>God is not mocked, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a man ſowes, that he ſhall reap.</hi> O beloved, Examine your ſelves, and try your ſelves; what is it you mind? what is it you ſeek? what is it you do? do you follow the Lamb in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, in his teachings, in his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in his Examples, &amp; through ſufferings and reproaches? have you forſaken all and followed him? <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.29. Have you taken up his Croſſe, and denyed your ſelves? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. Have you learned of him to be meek and lowly? <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. Have you viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and cloathed his Members? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35. Have you kiſſed the Sun, and made your peace with him? O belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, are you new Creatures? are you
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:99213:69"/>in Chriſt? are you in faith? <hi>Know ye not, if Chriſt be not in you, ye are repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates?</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> is for Exhortation.</p>
            <p>O Beloved, Let me beſeech you for your precious and immortal ſouls ſake, to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> from the Beaſts Image, and from his Worſhip, and from his Mark, that you may not be defiled: O come away to Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Ariſe my Love and come away,</hi> Cant. 2.10. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt,</hi> Mat. 11.28. Oh ſinners, he calls you to come to him; will you not go? we muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſin, and embrace vertue; put off the Old man, and put on the New man; we muſt have Repentance and Mortification, a dying unto ſin, and a living unto righteouſneſs; from the love of earthly things, to the deſire of heavenly things. Our bodies and ſouls muſt come away unto Chriſt; our ſouls, becauſe they are the Spouſe of Chriſt; our bodies, becauſe they are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt: We muſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:99213:70"/>come away from the Eenticements of the fleſh, the allurements of the world, and ſuggeſtions of the Divel, and from the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and from all the inventions and traditions of men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. That ye may walk with God, before God, after God, in the Name of God, and in the Spirit of God; And that we may live in Chriſt, as Chriſt lives in the Father. O what more happy then to live for ever? and ſo to live for ever, as Chriſt himſelf li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth? Surely that is a bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious life. This is a Believers life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Labour more and more to be like thoſe that follow the Lamb fully: they are very holy and pure; they are called Virgins,</p>
            <p>Firſt, For their Chaſtity: <hi>That I may preſent you as chaſt Virgins unto Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.2. Theſe love Chriſt with a chaſt, but not with an adulterous love.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For their purity: They are Virgin-Saints, they are not defiled with the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> but have kept themſelves from her Idolatry and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:99213:70"/>Superſtition, and from her ſin and wickedneſs; <hi>And in their mouth was found no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Believers are ſtiled and titled Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Chriſts Members are glorious Members; they are called Heaven for two Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe there is much of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe there is much of them in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is much of Heaven in Believers, much of God, much of Chriſt, and much of the Spirit: <hi>Of his fulneſs have all we received grace for grac,</hi> Joh. 1.16. The glory of God, the knowledge of God, the preſence of God, the love of God, the holineſs of God, the joyes of God; theſe are the things that make Heaven to be Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Now there is much of theſe in Believers, therefore they are called Heaven. We are taken into Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Angels, and our Communion with the Angels in a great meaſure doth conſiſt in bearing a part with
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:99213:71"/>them in praiſing God; it is the action of Heaven. Believers are holy Ones, and they have glorious Titles.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Lords Portion,</hi> Deut. 32.9.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His <hi>Pleaſant Portion,</hi> Jer. 12.10.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, His <hi>Inheritance,</hi> Iſa, 19.25.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The <hi>Dearly beloved of my ſoul,</hi> Jer. 12.7.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Gods <hi>Treaſure and peculiar Treaſure,</hi> Exod. 19.5.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, His <hi>Glory,</hi> Iſa. 46.13.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The <hi>Houſe of Gods glory,</hi> Iſa. 60.7.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, A <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> Iſa. 62.3.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, A <hi>Royal Diadem;</hi> in the ſame place.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, <hi>The Glory of God,</hi> Jer. 3.17.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, <hi>Golden Candleſticks,</hi> Rev. 1.12.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, <hi>Kings,</hi> Rev. 5.10. And in my Text, <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is as much difference between the Church of God and other men, as
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:99213:71"/>there is betwixt Gold and Dirt, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Diamonds and Pebbles, in the Lords eſteem; they are to God above all people: <hi>The righteous is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than his neighbour,</hi> Pro. 12.26. O how precious, how happy, how bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and glorious are Believers? they are called Heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Believers are called Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe there is much of them in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Their Thoughts are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.18.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Their Deſires are ie Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Their Affections are in Heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 3 2.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Their Hopes are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Their Converſations are in Heaven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Their Hearts are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.21.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Their Aims are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20.</p>
            <p>O there is much of Believers in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:99213:72"/>their ſouls are in heaven, when their bodies are walking upon the Earth; they live in heaven whil'ſt they are on the earth, and they come to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when they leave the earth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6. <hi>And hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> The Saints are ſet in heavenly places, heavenly Dignities, heavenly priviledges, heavenly Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives. The Saints of the High God, are ſet in high places. The true Church is that Spouſe that is fair and beautiful, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. O the Church of Chriſt is lovely and glorious:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, Glorious in her Head.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, Glorious in her Titles.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, Glorious in her Gifts and Graces.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, Glorious in her Offices.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly, Glorious in her Priviledges.</item>
                  <item>Sixthly, Glorious in her Members.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>O the Church of Chriſt is a holy Church, and a glorious Church: <hi>That he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinke, or
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:99213:72"/>any ſuch thing; but that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh,</hi> Epheſ. 5.27. <hi>They are not defiled, they are Virgins, and in their mouthes is found no guile. Now he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall exhort you that are members of this heavenly Church,</p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſeek Heavenly things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and above all things elſe; Let your hearts be filled with Heavenly knowledge, and heavenly riches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Delight in heavenly things, let it be your heaven upon Earth, to ſerve the God of heaven.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Act by Heavenly Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Have a holy dependance upon God,
<list>
                  <item>For Direction,</item>
                  <item>For Protection,</item>
                  <item>For Aſſiſtance,</item>
                  <item>For a bleſſing.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Eye Heavenly objects, God, Chriſt, and the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Imitate Heavenly Ones;
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:99213:73"/>follow them that follow Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Walk by a Heavenly Rule; walk according to the Laws of heaven.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, and laſtly, Live much in heaven.
<list>
                  <item>Your Father is in heaven,</item>
                  <item>Your Head is in Heaven,</item>
                  <item>Your Husband is in heaven,</item>
                  <item>Your King is in heaven,</item>
                  <item>Your Treaſure is in heaven,</item>
                  <item>Your Crown is in heaven,</item>
                  <item>Your Wages are in heaven.</item>
               </list> And where ſhould you be but in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; <hi>Knowing in your ſelves that ye have in heaven a better and an endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſubſtance,</hi> Heb. 10.34. <hi>For we know, that if our Earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, and a houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1.</p>
            <p>Oh theſe are bleſſed and holy ones: <hi>And they that are with him, are called, and choſen, and faithful,</hi> Rev. 17.14. Oh labour to be like theſe in purity,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:99213:73"/>and piety, in holineſs and humbleneſs, in meekneſs, and patience, in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and uprightneſs, in ſpiritualneſs and in all Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Follow the Lamb out of <hi>Babylon. And they cryed with a loud voice, ſaying, How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the Earth?</hi> Revel. 6.10. <hi>And another Angel came out of the Temple, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a loud voice to him that ſat on the Cloud, Thruſt in thy Sicle and reap, for the time is come for thee to reap, for the harveſt of the Earth is ripe. And he that ſat on the Cloud thruſt in his Sicle on the earth, and the earth was reaped. And another Angel came out of the Temple which is in heaven, he alſo having a ſharp Sicle,</hi> Rev. 14.15, 16, 17. The Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed with a double deſtruction:
<list>
                  <item>Her walls ſhall fall down:</item>
                  <item>Her wall of Power;</item>
                  <item>Her wall of Policy;</item>
                  <item>Her wall of Superſtition;</item>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:99213:74"/>
                  <item>Her wall of Maintenance:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe ſhe hath corrupted Religion, and that both in Doctrine and Worſhip. <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great City, becauſe ſhe made all Nations drink of the Wine of the wrath of her fornication,</hi> Rev. 14.8. Chap. 18.3.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe ſhe hath poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Kings of the Earth. The Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath been the great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Kings. <hi>And I ſaw three unclean ſpirits like Frogs, come out of the mouth of the Dragon, and out of the mouth of the Beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe Prophet; for they are the ſpirits of Devils working miracles, which go forth unto the Kings of the Earth, and of the whole world, to gather them to the battle of that great day of God Almighty,</hi> Rev. 16.13.14. Chap. 17.2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For her cruelty: <hi>In her was found the blood of the Prophets, and all the Saints that were ſlain upon the Earth,</hi> Chap. 18.24. <hi>And I ſaw the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:99213:74"/>woman drunken with the blood of the ſaints, and with the blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Jeſus; and when I ſaw her I wondred with great admiration,</hi> Chap. 17.6.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Becauſe her ruine and deſtruction is publiſhed and proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over the world. <hi>And he cryed migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily with a ſtrong voice, ſaying,</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <hi>the great is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of Devils,</hi> Chap. 18.2. Chap. 14.8.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is the great deſign that Chriſt hath in the latter dayes of the world to deſtroy Antichriſt. <hi>The Lamb ſhall overcome them, for he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings,</hi> Cha. 17.14. <hi>His eyes were as a flame of fire, and on his head were many Crowns, and he was cleathed with a Veſture dipt in blood, and his name is called, The Word of God: And out of his mouth goeth a ſharp ſword, that with it he ſhould ſmite the Nations,</hi> Chap. 19.12, 13, 15.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Becauſe ſhe hath greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted and triumpht over the Lords
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:99213:75"/>people in their miſeries and calamities. <hi>And they that dwell upon the Earth ſhall rejoyce over them, and make merry, and ſend gifts one to another,</hi> Rev. 11.10.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Becauſe of all the Churches enemies that ever were, this is the cruelleſt enemy. The fourth Beaſt is worſe than any of the former Beaſts: <hi>And behold, a fourth Beaſt, dreadfull and terrible, and ſtrong exceedingly, and it had great Iron teeth, and it was divers from all the Beaſts that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it,</hi> Dan. 7.7. Rev. 18.24.</p>
            <p>Eightly, It is the expectation of all the Saints that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and thrown like a Mil-ſtone, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.21. Now God that hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this expectation in the hearts of his people, he will not fruſtrate their expectation, he will fulfill their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, God hath promiſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſcarlet Whore, becauſe ſhe hath deſtroyed his Saints, and ſhe is to be rewarded as ſhe hath rewarded others, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.5, 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.8.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:99213:75"/>
            <p>Tenthly, The Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, becauſe ſhe truſteth in the arm of fleſh, and glorieth in her ſtrength, and riches. <hi>How much ſhe hath glorified her ſelf, and lived deliciouſly, ſo much torment and ſorrow give her; for ſhe ſaith in her heart, I ſit a Queen, I am no Widdow, and ſhall ſee no ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: therefore ſhall her plagues come,</hi> Chap. 18.7. Now Beloved, conſider of this, and think of this, and keep your ſelves from <hi>Babylon,</hi> that ye do not partake of her ſins, leaſt ye receive of her plagues, O poor ſinners, if you have any love to your Souls, if you have any mind to be ſaved, follow the Lamb, that you may be ſaved by the Lamb.</p>
            <p>He leads poor ſouls from darkneſs to light,
<list>
                  <item>From death to life,</item>
                  <item>From vice to vertue,</item>
                  <item>From Satan to God,</item>
                  <item>From poverty to plenty,</item>
                  <item>From ſorrow to joy,</item>
                  <item>From miſery to glory,</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99213:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <item>From an earthly Kingdom, to a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom,</hi> Mat. 25.34.</p>
            <p>O the Kingdom which Chriſt leads poor ſouls to, is,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt; A Rich Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, A peaceable Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, A Righteous Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>Fourdily, A bleſſed Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly, A Glorious Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>Sixthly, A ſatisfying Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>Seventhly, A Univerſal Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>Eighthly, An Everlaſting Kingdom.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Oh follow the Lamb, follow the Lamb, that you may be for ever glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with the Lamb, and by the Lamb.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99213:76"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
